[music]
Hey.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Ask Kabijit show. I
hope you're all doing great. Today we
will discuss any topic that you want.
I'll take as many questions as possible
from the super chat and also if possible
the regular chat and uh before we get
going as always let us see who all is
there on the live chat this fine evening
or day or morning wherever you are. I
can see KS11. Bascar Bandit Bascar
Bandit uh Gajapati Dave Hello YTPI2GC
geopolitical Dubai is here from Indor.
Good evening sir. Ravi moan Shubam Vavar
Sabari Schneider
Duv Duv Ary Manhattan real painter even
tithe sir.
Uh Shishir Upad Mna Kotari Adwit Ashmani
Mitesh Namar Tadas Namaste
Shat Bish Hello. Uh who else do we have?
Wagada namaste. Ain hello Aravind.
Uh Karan Nalawad Jam good to see you
sir. Karan Nalawad G. Prashant Bharat
Namitas once again. Vikash PJ hello good
to have you. Arya X7X namaste.
Um abinovish pashant the conqueror v
good good evening sir crazy brain good
to see you good to see you mac for J1
onlinear mahadev g i sager dani good to
have you sirishra
vidi nay good vidar good to have you
ma'am good to see you again as always we
have Amisha G always good to have Amisha
G hello good evening ma'am da joti gope
vikash pj Manhattan uh sukun
Sukun Verer Hello Sesh Nail YT Hello
Sesh Nal YT Hello sir Shan Bharat
Gata Saptasi
Gata Sapasati All right that's a new
avatar that you have ma'am good to have
you humanity survives
Galawad here is Narendra from Tokyo from
Toronto good morning Narendra from
Toronto good to have you Rahul AK hello
mvin69 good evening good to see
Minimalist Maverick once again study
vlogs is Dshant from Jarkand India.
Chhattabish says cold afternoon here.
Well, I wish you warmth. Author Santo
Rana Zodiac cycle. Uh who else do we
have? The conqueror once again.
Goautami. Good evening. Goautami G. Uh
Vitri Martinez. Hello. Uh Saga Gajati
Dave Ashoto Kalyan Chakraarti. Hello.
Jay Dakshit. Hello. Good to see you. Um
and so many people so many other people.
Nirvana Shanks Kuriasan Kuricha Clash of
Clan. Hello. Naman Sudinav Mishra Tju
Mata. Hello. Um Vijay Vagela Kimcho.
Yes. Kimcho Majama indeed. Yes sir. The
sky prime namaskar g namaskar sha
smithra is here from Moscow. Vinay Ry
Vin Ray from Azamar and everybody else.
I won't be able to greet you all
individually all of you but good to have
you all of you. Thank you. Thank you so
much for being on the live stream and
now let's get going with the questions.
What questions do we have for today?
Question number one is from Mr. Bhaskar
Bandit Pyat Pyat Sar.
Um in the past we discussed poverty
glorification in Bharat after 1947 in
media in politics in cinema. uh one
reason being that uh being the Naruvian
socialist policies yes but was it the
same for the USSR maestina or 1960s Cuba
I can't think of any other nation you
know great nation great as in
substantial nation where you've had the
glorification of poverty if you watch
the movies oft
I mean a lot of people are immediately
start going to disagree with that he's a
great guy and great director, one of the
greatest of all time. Maybe he got an
Oscar and all and so on. But what I saw
I mean you know I saw a few of his
movies at least some parts as a kid and
all I saw was the abject poverty that he
would depict in every movie. So that's
one example. There's many other Indian
filmmakers who depict just abject
poverty and just misery in India. And
then you have all the western filmmakers
like you know what what what's that
movie? Slum Dog Millionaire
and lots of other movies. I remember
this movie. I mean,
there's this movie, okay, it's called
Out of Africa. It's a 1980s movie. I
probably saw it dubbed in French or
something.
And there's this character in the movie.
What was what was the character's name?
So, the character is is a waiter or a
bartender. Mostly most likely a waiter.
His name is Rajie.
And Rajie is a waiter. Do you remember
who was India's prime minister in the
1980s? It was Rajie Gandhi. So they
created this fictional character in this
movie out of Africa which is based on
real story. In this fictional fictional
character is a waiter named Rajie who
played the waiter Kabir Bi.
So they the west has always sought to
you know denigrate India and especially
with the glorification of poverty and so
on. Today if you visit India, if you're
a foreign tourist, you're going to visit
slums. You're going to have Indian tour
agencies organizing visits to slums. And
even if you don't have a visit to the to
a slum, they will try and look out for
the for the patches of of of poverty and
misery in India, they'll go with the
cameras and they'll intrude into
people's lives and click away, click
away, click away.
Yeah. So that's the that's the thing. So
I cannot think of any other country, any
other great substantial country where
you've had this. I can't think I mean
Cuba is not a great substantial country.
I'm not saying it's not great. Nice
people and so on. But you know, you
don't see the glorification of poverty
in Cuba. You can see the exoticization
of Cuba for sure. Cuba is stuck in the
1960s because of American sanctions and
all. And today American tourists who
visit there will you know go tick tick
at the vintage cars and vintage vintage
buildings and so on but they don't
glorify poverty there. They'll do it in
Africa. Sure. But Africa is genuinely in
abject poverty because of the last two
centuries two and a half centuries of
European colonization which still
continues actually. Um if they if
westerners went to the USSR well first
of all the USSR never allowed Westerners
to go into places where you had anything
that would show the USSR in bad light.
So it wasn't the case in the USSR. In
China, once again, the government
controlled everything. No western was
allowed to go and and do anything that
would tarnish China's image. But in
India, we we welcome it ourselves.
Please come visit our slums. Please
visit our misery. Please showcase our
misery. And that's there's lot of
Indians who showcase India's misery.
It's it's part of the ongoing saga of
the Indian inferiority complex, the
Indian slave mentality.
First of all, Indians need to come up to
overcome this. Then we can talk about
pointing fingers at the west. Indians
themselves like to exoticize the poverty
and the misery of India. I mean, yeah,
I'll not say anything beyond that
because I could say much more, but then
people get upset. So, we'll end there.
Baser Bandit says, why is there fear
around the EU of nuclear energy to power
cities and to generally generate power?
Why is there um why is there fear? We
know it's clean, highly efficient, 2 to
5% lowenriched uranium does not pose a
threat to cities and might there be
alleged lobbies that push or fund the
sphere.
So when it comes to the when it comes to
uranium, which is typically the fuel
that you use in nuclear reactors, uh
natur the the uranium that occurs
naturally in nature, it's typically less
than 1% uranium 235. So there are
multiple isotopes of uranium. An isotope
is an atom of an element that contains a
varying number of neutrons with the same
number of protons and electrons. Okay,
basic chemistry or basic physics. So,
uranium comes in multiple flavors of
isotopes. Uranium 235, 238 and so on.
238. Yeah. Yeah. 238. So, uh
your naturally occurring uranium is
about less than 1% uranium 235. The rest
is mostly 238 but low enrich uranium is
between
3 to 20% uranium 235. So you you've got
to process the thing and make it you
know you know uh enhance the the
percentage of uranium 235 to between 3
to 20%. That's lowenriched uranium. Then
you have highlyenriched uranium that is
up to 80%. And then you have something
called weapons grade very naughty
uranium that's above 90 95%. 235.
So when it comes to the uranium that's
used in nuclear reactors, typically
um standard nuclear reactors, let's say,
you typically have 3 to 5% uranium 235.
Okay? And that does not pose a threat to
cities. Well,
even highly enriched uranium does not
pose threat to you to to cities if you
handle it carefully, if you are
professional, if you if you get your
things right. So it's not about the
level of enrichment. Even uranium 238 is
radioactive. Even that can pose health
hazards. So it's not about the
enrichment, the percentage of
enrichment. It's about whether your
whether the operation you're running,
the nuclear nuclear reactor you've
designed and constructed is safe or not.
And if you look at the past what we've
had nuclear reactors since 1945,
probably before 45. Yeah. The first one
Manhattan project. So let's say 45
onwards that's that's how many years
that's 81 years now you had nuclear
reactors how many accidents have we had
we've had nine what three mile island we
had uh cherobil we had fukushma
that's what I can think of and there
must have been some you know lower
intensity accidents here and there
incidents
and it's only chernobbile that caused a
major problem and Fukushima to an extent
and 3m island did not cause that much of
an issue. Um, so why is there so much
fear-mongering about this? For example,
France, what percentage of France energy
comes from nuclear? I think 60 70% at
least, right? Um, and France has never
had any issue. Uh, let's Google this.
What percentage uh what
percentage of France
uh energy is nuclear? Yeah, France is
energy. Yes. 65 to 70%. Can you believe
it?
Can you believe it? Imagine that. No cur
coal burning, no nothing. Just nuclear,
clean nuclear, completely green. As long
as you're doing it professionally,
there's no issue ever. So why would
there be lobbies and and fearmongers and
all? Well, that's because if you have
sufficient nuclear energy generation
capabilities, then you become genuinely
independent in terms of energy at least
for electricity purposes. Yeah. And
there will be people who don't want
India to achieve this sort of thing. And
that's why you will have fear-mongering.
Basker Bandit says, "We use fishision on
earth for energy purposes. Can't do
fusion yet. But can say space-based
fusion be done within the realm of
physics as a means of energy production
away from Earth itself?" Well,
space-based fusion is all over the
place. Every star is space-based fusion.
Fusion reactor, isn't it? It's a
gigantic ginormous fusion reaction. But
we are talking about controlled fusion
that is initiated by humans and
controlled by humans. Well,
uh, we would rather want to do it on
Earth first. I mean, transporting the
equipment and all that stuff to space
and then testing out fusion whether we
can ignite it or not. I mean, it's it's
impractical.
Um,
fusion will first whenever it happens,
sustained fusion reaction will be first
done on earth itself. Maybe in the next
20 years, maybe 5 to 20 years. Yeah,
most likely within 20 years we will have
controlled fusion.
Yeah, probably by by 2050 we will have
the first bulky whatever fusion reactors
stokamax or whatever. Yeah. Um
so
earthbased fusion is very much possible
within the realm of physics and once we
can do it on earth we can also do it on
space I suppose. Yeah. And you can use
that to generate energy from away from
earth but it will first be done on
earth. It is not dangerous as such. It's
not going to cause a nuclear explosion
or whatever. Yeah. So it's it's um if
people are fear mongering about nuclear
reactors and the potential dangers of
nuclear reactors in case there's a
meltdown or something uncontrolled um
break up you know runaway chain reaction
or whatever for whatever reason that can
cause problems which is a very very very
rare which is a very rare chance of
occurring. Well a fusion reaction will
be way less dangerous even if it goes
runway and you know there's a breach of
the containment vessel or whatever. Uh
so it's definitely within the realm of
physics. Fusion happens. We know it
happens. It's just about how do we
control it. So it's not a physics
problem. It's an engineering problem.
Getting a fusion reaction to be
self-sustaining and generate a net
positive power output. That will first
happen on earth and then on space maybe
in the future much much later. Ken Kane
says why does India not why does India
not have something like the Monroe
doctrine or some ambitious doctrine? I
mean such big aspirations during its
inceptions made the US the world power
today.
Yeah. Why does India not have this?
Well, when the US came up with the
Mandro doctrine in 19 in 1823,
um there was no great power in the
western hemisphere. The US
was the power and the other powers were
the European nations that sought to
influence and control the the western
hemisphere, the Americas. So the US says
said we will not tolerate this anymore
and initially they were not powerful
enough to prevent European nations from
meddling in the affairs of let's say
central uh the central American region
or South America but eventually they got
got more and more powerful over over the
decades and eventually they were in a
position where nobody would dare
interfere in the western hemisphere in
the Americas North America South America
Central America. So they had the vision
in 1823 that one day we will become so
powerful nobody will be able to dare
bother us or or you know meddal in the
western hemisphere took them maybe a
century to do that but they started
working on it. Now what would a Mandro
doctrine like thing look look for India?
We could start with the subcontinent
that nobody will be allowed to interfere
in the matters of the subcontinent
whether it's India, Pakistan,
Afghanistan, Nepal, Bangladesh, Bhutan,
Sri Lanka, Maldives or Burma. Let's
include Burmal for example even though
it's part of Southeast Asia but
hypothetically. So let's say India puts
forth this doctrine. Let's call it the
Chava doctrine. No one's allowed to
interfere
in the affairs of the subcontinent
except for India. So let's say we come
up with this doctrine. Today we aren't
able to enforce it. Today we aren't able
to enforce the Chavda doctrine because
right now in the subcontinent the most
powerful actor is the United States.
It's not India. That's that's a fact.
The US is more powerful in our own
backyard than us.
But let's say this is an aspirational
doctrine. that in 10 years time we will
operationalize this and we will prevent
anybody no matter who it is from
interfering whether it's the US whether
it's China or whoever else maybe you
know apart from alien invaders nobody
else will be allowed to do this so maybe
we have something like this but we
haven't inunciated that maybe we haven't
publicized that
you know
see when the US put up put up the Mundo
doctrine there was no global superpower
who could have squashed the US for
showing any signs of ambition. There was
nobody. So they did so that so so they
did that. Today we have a global
superpower that seeks to squash India's
ambitions
and and and prevent curtail India's
growth. There's a nation global
superpower who seeks to contain India
and the next 5 years are going to be
make or break for India. We are at that
position today my dear friends. By 2030
we will know whether India is going to
be a great power or India is going to be
once again a vasal like it was for two
and a half centuries during the East
India Company days next five years we'll
decide that so right now even we if we
have
an ambition
such as the Monro doctrant we're going
to keep it very quiet okay
Mr. Then Shaoping was right when he said
hide your strengths, hide your ambitions
and bide your time. Work, work, work.
Keep quiet. Keep your heads down. Stop
boasting.
Don't boast. Don't publicize what your
intentions are. Don't publicize your
strengths. Just keep quiet and keep
working. So
I think we may have something like that
or maybe we don't. What whatever. I I I
couldn't possibly know. But in case we
have it, we we we'll keep very quiet
about it. We will have to keep very
quiet about it for the next five years
at least. Yeah, that's the deal. Now the
common public in India will be very
upset. We need strong statements. We
need a master stroke. We want to show
them what we are and so on. No, take it
easy. Take it easy. Be patient. That's
my recommendation to everybody. Basar
Bandit says, "What's the history of
Bengal area pre-British and Islamic
occupation? We know Buddhism rose. Well,
yeah, it rose.
But what else was going on in the past
2,000 years here? Gandhar and Pakistan
land mass is often discussed but not
this Bengal. So Bengal is historic
Bangladesh of Bangladesh, right? Past
2,000 years, what did we have? We had
the gold kingdom. Gold kingdom, gold
empire. The last great king was
Shashank. King Shashank. So the gold
kingdom was from what? the 4th century
to the 8th century, 7th 8th century
around that time it was pretty
substantial. It included present day
Bengal which is east and west Bengal
both also parts of Magad etc.
So that is the God kingdom. The great
king was king Shashank right. Um how
many Bengales
are proud of King Shashank today. I
wonder
how many Bengales remember King Shashank
and and write about his glories and
speak about his the great deeds he did.
I wonder how many I wonder why. Then
after the the dissolution of the of the
gold kingdom, we had about a century or
so in the in that region in in in our
region Bengal where you had anarch
you know we had little petty king
chieftains, petty little warlords or or
chiefs who would snipe at each other,
fight each other and there was no rule
of law or there was no rule of law,
there was no law, there was no order,
there was mats
matsai
is one big fish eat small fish, dog eat
dog. Absolute anarchy, chaos and
disaster for people. So the people got
together in Bengal. They said we're
going to now elect a king of our own. We
will decide who's going to be king. We
will elect a king democratically. So
they got together
and elected a king.
So who comes? This was the Pala king,
right? King Gopal. King Gopal
who probably was an ordinary person. He
was elected the king of Bengal of the
region and there was the rise of the
pala pala dynasty empire the pala empire
and it was in power until the 12th
century or something
and then you have various other kingdoms
that come and go etc and then you have
well the more recent history so the
history of Bengal is great it's glorious
it was a tremendously prosperous region
beautiful region beautiful art culture
uh so much for great contributions to
our civilization overall in the in the
big picture right so much so much great
uh institutions of learning vikram
mashila vikram sheila was in present day
west east Pakistan was it let's see
vikramila university okay it's in modern
day bihar so which oneapuri
um ancient University
in Bangladesh.
Which one was it? Jagadala Mahavihar,
Somur Mahavihar.
Yeah. Pandit and so on. So, so what is
now East Pakistan also had these
wonderful amazing institutions of
learning and so much more. So, I mean
this region is huge and the history is
great. It's it's it's great. It's it's
rich. It's detailed and uh yeah it's
it's hard to discuss that in in a few
minutes but there's tremendous
incredibly rich ancient history when it
comes to Bengal but today all that we
speak they speak about is what communism
and uh whatever happened in the past 100
years or
today our our historians will extol the
glories
um
of of of whatever
Bengales did under British occupation.
But what about the Bengales who who did
while Bengal while while while our
civilization was free? That nobody talks
about which is weird.
Baskar Bandit says, "Can we expect a
balconized Iran in the coming weeks with
multiple groups seeking separation
considering the diverse ethnicities
within the existing borders of Iran?
It could happen anytime. I suppose we
have to keep see if you want to if you
want to predict what happens, you have
to keep an eye in real time on whether
the Americans are building up an
invasive force in the region in the
vicinity.
Okay. So for example uh before we we saw
the US uh intervention regime change in
Venezuela and the abduction of
Venezuela's president by the Americans
before that happened in the couple of
two three months before that the
Americans built up this entire um force
structure around Venezuela in the region
right aircraft carriers warships what
not so you could see something's going
to happen it was it was clearly imminent
some kind of US military action was
imminent and then we saw it
before you had the uh the invasion of
Iraq in 1991, you know, desert storm or
whatever they called it. Before that
happened, the Americans built up a
gigantic invas invasive force in the
region, right? Because there are plenty
of American bases and other and bases of
vasal states in the region in the West
Asia region. So for example, let's look
at US bases
in Middle East. We call they call it the
Middle East. We call it West Asia. Let's
go to image. So here we have American
bases in the Middle East and you can see
how many of these are deployed along the
the Persian Gulf, right? You can see
that
uh what do we have here? I'm not sure
what that shows you. I mean are they
claiming okay now this is
and they so the Americans have this
force posture in the Middle East but
they also have the the added advantage
of Pakistan being a US vasal state now
and they can use all the Pakistani bases
to attack Iran from the eastern flank so
Iran is now
it's facing
potential American action from the south
from the west as well as from the east
yeah if it happens So the question is,
is the US building up a force posture in
the region? If it does that, it'll do it
very quietly.
So,
so I'm not sure if that's happening. I'm
hearing rumors that something like that
will be happening. You know, a large
transport aircraft are being mobilized
towards this region and so on. So maybe
it may take time. Maybe it may happen
suddenly. We don't know.
But I don't expect a bulcanized Iran. If
the Americans or when the Americans
attempt a regime change, if it is
successful in Iran, it will not give
rise to a bulcanized Iran. It will give
rise to a unified Iran under a US puppet
government. That's what we can expect if
it happens or when it happens.
Shubam var says is India going through a
phase of dharmasut now there's no
dharmas dhas
well India is not a dharmic nation
anymore India is a secular nation
whatever the hell that means so dharma
is constantly under sankut that's for
sure but if you're asking about the
choices India is faced with and all
there's no dharmasut the choices are
clear be free sovereign independent and
strong or be a vasal there is no dharma
in this maybe at different levels there
may be various other
elements of dharma sanank which we don't
need to go into over here the Chinese
ensure that they don't have any dharma
they take actions specific actions that
eliminate the possibility of dhmas by
taking actions against potentially
compromised u members of the Chinese
communist party in the case of India we
never do that so maybe
uh sabarish na says India walked out of
the industry post operation sindur since
the US backs Pakistan a lot. Why didn't
didn't the US sanction India or put
pressure on India to release the water?
The US doesn't care what happens to the
people of Pakistan.
That's why the US has also walked out of
treaties unilaterally. Just recently
when Donald Trump was the 45th
president, he unilaterally walked out of
the JCPOA, the Iran nuclear deal
unilaterally because he felt like the
Chinese
also reasonably recently walked out of
their deal with the UK about the status
of Hong Kong, right? They walked out of
the deal unilaterally. We don't care. We
don't agree to this anymore because we
don't want to by our choice. So the
point is every nation has the right to
walk out of any agreement it has signed
if it is no longer in its interests. We
are not duty bound to abide by interests
by abide by agreements that harm us or
are count contraind you know that run
counter to our interests. No nation is
obligated to put up with agreements that
hurt or harm its interests or run
counter to its interests unless that
nation is a vasal of somebody. In that
case, you can force that nation at
gunpoint to do whatever. But that's not
the case for us.
And does it if you walk out of the
India's water treaty and start building
the infrastructure to divert the waters
of the these rivers and so on, does it
hurt American interests? They don't. No,
it doesn't hurt American interests. They
can still use Pakistan for all the all
the purposes they need Pakistan for.
Maybe it makes Pakistan more eager to
serve US interests.
Right. Right. It may actually make
Pakistan more eager, more ammonable to
serving American interests against
India. So why would the the Americans do
anything? It's good for them.
YT says I'm from Bangalore. Bangaluru.
Whenever I see there's wherever I see
there's US fast food chains all across
Bangaluru. You may not be wrong at all.
Do you think this is a US deep state
plan to make Indians unhealthy? Make
sure that in the next 10 years there's
more unhealthy Indians that can be which
can strain the economy. Well, I'm not
sure if it's a deep state plan, but
yeah, it helps if India is uh riddled
with American fast food chains that uh
put trans fats in your body and
processed foods in your body and god
knows what kind of chemicals in your
body and make you obese and unhealthy
and uh up the risk of cardiovascular
disease and diabetes and obesity and
Alzheimer's disease and god knows what
else. Why not? It's great for the US,
right? I mean, they're doing that for to
their own citizens, first of all.
There's no question about that. Their
citizens are the unhealthiest in the
world and they would like to export that
fantastic American culture everywhere
else. Uh but a lot of this has to do
with the Indian slave mentality. A lot
of this has to do with Indian India's
mental colonization and the inferiority
complex and slave mentality of Indians.
I went and ate burger. I eat pizza. I
No, not pizza. Pizza. I ate pizza. I ate
burger. I ate western food. See, I'm so
advanced.
That's what Indians feel that if you
want to show that you're hip and you're
cool, then you must eat Western food,
you must eat at expensive fast food
restaurants that have American brands on
top, you know, on on the on the board.
That's what lots of Indians feel. And
these foods are very easy to make,
right? I mean, they're they're
mass-produced like sausages.
So, that's the deal.
So it does you you're seeing an increase
in in Indians being more and more
unhealthy because of this because we've
moved away from our traditional diets
and that that applies to everybody
actually. So I don't think it's a deep
state plan overall but it does tie in
with the interests of the deep state or
or the United States overall.
Rohi moan says it turns out that many of
our top Bollywood songs are copied from
Arabic and Turkish songs and even some
movies without giving credits to the
originals. Any thoughts on this
practice?
I am not aware of Arabic and Turkish
songs. Maybe I can show you some
examples. Okay, let's Google
you see one of the greatest Bollywood
singers playback singers of all time is
Kishor Kumar. Now let's Google
Kishorkumar
Lord
Shorty.
Have you heard of Shorty? Lord Shorty Om
Shanti Om. Who was Lord Shorty? Ras
Shorty born Garfield black man also
known as Lord Shorty was a Trinidadian
calypso and SOA musician known as the
father of SOA and the love man. Uh Ras
Shorty the first. So yeah, he was a a
Trinidadian singer. Now he wrote and
performed the song Omshanti or Omshanti
Om.
Okay. Uh Kishor Kumar Lord Shorty
um
uh copied song.
So
Kishar Kumar's hit song Mary Omar Kojan
Om Shanti Om from the film Cars is is
known it's not widely believed it's
known to be stolen from from Lord
Shorty's
1974 song Shanti Om Lord Shorty said
that he gave Kishor Kumar a copy of his
album and then the Kurs music directors
which is Kishar Kumar stole it.
So and so I believe that this was Kishar
Kumar song but turns out that this guy
Lord Shorty when Kishar Kumar visited
the Caribbean he had gifted a copy of
his album to Kishar Kumar and a few
months later he hears his own song
transformed into a Bollywood song Om
Shanti Omjano
etc and sung by Keshar Kumar I mean
imagine the lack of ethics it takes I I
was a great admirer of Kishumar until I
found this
That's is just one example. Have you
heard of [laughter] Elvis Presley and
Margarita?
Elvis Presley.
Margarita.
Well, I would recommend listen to this
song
and that will immediately remind you of
a very famous Hindi song from I don't
know 60s, 1960s, 1970s.
Yeah.
Conjoy
or something
Opria or yeah or Margarita Opria that
sort of thing. There are so many
Bollywood songs that have been lifted
just just blatantly from western music,
western songs, I don't know, Arabic,
Turkish, whatever. See, after Bollywood
became more and more
West Asianized or Middle Easternized,
that's when Bollywood uh singers and and
musicians started copying Arabic and
Turkish songs.
From the 1970s, 80s onwards, Bollywood
became more and more West Asian or
Middle Eastern in in in culture, right?
Before that, it was all stealing from
the west. And I'm sure after that also,
so there's so many examples of of these
these these unethical practices in
Bollywood. And at that time, India was
like North Korea completely cut off from
the rest of the world. So Indians would
never know that so and so was stolen
from so- and so place. the rest of the
world would know but Indians would never
know and as far as as long as Indians
don't know these people didn't care they
didn't care that they are they they are
you know denigrating the the name and
and and reputation of India globally
they didn't care at all these people as
long as they made some money from the
ticket sales and whatnot in India and
India was completely cut off from the
rest of the world your news I mean you
had one television station Dur Dashan
which would transmit four hours a day
two news sessions in which all they
would say is what minister did said what
today nothing was would be reported
about what was happening outside outside
the country so India was closed off w
garden just like North Korea
until 1991 '92 or whatever and that's
that after 91192 that's when people
started realizing slowly that all these
songs have been copied so that's really
shameful yeah what are my thoughts on
this practice deplorable shameful
I lost a lot of respect for people who
for the great singers like Kishor Kumar
and so on who did such things. Terrible.
Okay. Arvin says it's said that uh the
first skyscraper city was built by
medieval Yemenite Arabs in the 15th
century. Is this really true? Yeah.
There there
Manhattan of of the Middle East or
something it's called, right? I forget
the name. Manhattan of Arabia.
Uh Shibbam. The city of Shebam.
Manhattan of the desert.
15th. So it's not the 15th century. It's
like 12th century or something. This is
what the these buildings still stand
today. They're multi-storyried
buildings. And uh as you can see, it
looks like some some modernday congested
city or something, right? But this was
built several centuries ago. Uh it's in
it's in Yemen. Okay. Sheam. And when was
this constructed? Um, city was founded
in the 3rd century. History, blah, blah,
culture, truth, rest, geography,
climate, influence. Come on, man. When
did when were the buildings built?
Um,
not sure. So, was this in the 15th
century like you say? Was it before?
I am not sure. I think if you if we go
into the details and spend some time
reading, we may get some idea. But yeah,
so it's the city of Sheibbam, the town
of Sheibbam.
Okay. Next, Dhu Ria says, "I want to
have a debate with you on the Arian
migration." All right, sir. Uh,
everybody wants to have a debate with me
on the aran migration. I can't spare the
time for everybody. And my views on the
Arian mig like you say migration. So,
you are a believer in the migration
theory. Well, all the best, sir. Good
for good for you. It's fine. Uh, if you
disagree with me, that's fine. But, uh,
I will not have the time to have a
debate with you, sir. But uh yeah, I
mean look, if you are have very strong
opinions about this theory, then maybe
you can write about it. Maybe you can
make a YouTube video about it. And uh
but we'll see, right? So I can't have a
debate with everybody who wants to have
a debate with me. I actually do not have
debates with anybody. I don't believe in
having debates because it actually at
the end of the day doesn't solve any
issue, right? It's just about who comes
up on top. Snake is mad. I am not in
that business. So all right anyway sir
all the best. Ritik B says so only
Russia can stand up against the US
militarily.
You tell me. You tell me. You all tell
me. What do we see right now? The US
ruled over Venezuela.
They went in, kidnapped, abducted the
president and his wife. Just walked out.
What happened? What could China do?
Nothing. What could Russia do? Nothing.
What about the tanker, oil tanker that
the Americans captured? Russian oil
tanker in in in in the Atlantic. What
could Russia do? Nothing.
In Ukraine,
Russia retaliated and went to war.
So Russia can retaliate in a specific
specific certain region which is the
Russian sphere of influence
within Russia's red lines. Beyond that,
Russia can't even actually it is not it
doesn't make sense for Russia to even
retaliate. So at least Russia has gone
to war and the war is essentially a
proxy war that is being waged against
Russia by the Americans in the west.
So Russia can actually stand up to the
US militarily, but only in a specific
geography, not in the Atlantic, not in
the Pacific, not somewhere else,
only in Russia's vicinity.
Russia is a hard retaliator. China
China prefers to stand behind others and
make statements. China prefers to
respond economically or or or or you
know, put export restrictions on rare
earths. and so on. Those sort of
retaliations which are also hard
retaliations but not as hard as military
retaliation.
China dares not go to war with the US
because it stands to lose everything.
China has built up its economy over
decades of tremendous hard work that has
to be respected
and China doesn't want that to be wiped
out. even 20% or 10% of that to be wiped
out which would be a huge blow to China
and the US can do that and the US can't
be hit on its home soil it's too far
away and too risky so the Chinese prefer
to retaliate through other means not
military means only Russia has the has
the
gall has the hutsp
yes has the hoodspah has the has the
guts let's today to stand up to the US
militarily. Nobody else does right now.
Which is why like I have correctly said,
Russia is way more powerful than China
from a hard power perspective. Colin
Kane says technology has advanced, not
human nature. Ancient texts show people
were as intelligent as we are today.
Which is why humans keep repeating the
same mistakes. Is I g that's why we
should read history. Yeah, we should
read history. It makes a lot of sense to
read history because that teaches us
about human nature. It teaches us what
humans did in the past, our ancestors,
our forebears did centuries ago,
millennia ago. And it shows us
they were just like what we are today.
We haven't changed and the cycles of
history repeat themselves over and over
again, right? And the people for example
who wrote the Vedas I would say were
more intelligent than you and me.
Okay? to come up with that a priority
originally to come up with those
original thoughts. I mean imagine the
intelligence and the intellect and the
insights it takes to do that. So maybe
our ancestors were probably possibly
more intelligent than us, way more
intelligent than us, right? So that's
why I agree that we should study history
to understand these things you know that
keeps you grounded. [laughter]
Okay?
Shatabish says can human need to feel
appreciated in in life be instinctive or
a natural brain process or an outcome of
external seeding that's being told,
thought, upbringing etc. The human need
to feel appreciated in life. Is it
something that we are taught or is it
something instinctive that's ingrained
in us? I think everyone's born with this
need to be appreciated in some shape or
form.
There are many people who are desperate
for approval who want everybody to
approve of them. There are some people
who need approval but from the right
people and they don't care about
approval from just about anybody else.
Some people need a need some kind of
reassurance or some kind of approval
from a few people and some there are
very few humans who don't care about
anyone's approval. So the the
overwhelming majority of human beings
need some kind of approval at least from
some people in their life. Right? Is
this something that's taught? It's not
something that's taught. It's something
that's that that comes from deep within.
I don't know if it's a brain process or
what specifically it is because we don't
understand the brain in that detail. uh
but it is definitely something it's an
instinct or it's a need a basic
fundamental deep rooted human need that
seems to be born with us the moment we
are born right the need for connection
the need for human
human warmth human love you know the the
need to be to feel appreciated the need
for approval all of these because we
humans are a social species we are ired
to be social. We need to be part of an
integrated network of other human
beings. That's part of our instinct.
It's part of our programming or deep
brain programming, deep DNA programming,
whatever it is. That's why it's it's
something that's inborn. It's not
something that we learn.
Rahul says, "What are the similarities
and differences between preWorld War I,
PreWorld War II, preWorld War I, and
now?"
Um I would say that
the present day scenario is more similar
to the preWorld War I scenario where
there's a lot of instability there.
There's a lot of rearrangement of the
world order. There's a cold war like
situation which existed after after 1871
all the way to 1914
and then there was the Balkcon wars
which is kind of the Ukraine war
scenario that sort of thing. So there's
more similarities between now and World
War I, preWorld War I than now and
preWorld War II. The preWorld War II era
was this beaten nation that sought
that sought justice.
This this nation that was humiliated
that sought some kind of redressal for
that humiliation which is Germany. We
don't have that situation right now. We
are we have more of a preWorld War I
like situation right now, right? So
everything is in flux.
There are multiple powerful nations
right now. There's one overwhelmingly
more powerful nation, the US. At that
time it was the UK, right? Uh and there
are emerging powers. You had Japan that
was emerging. There was there Germany
that's emerging. At the time Japan
emerged suddenly later on preWorld War I
it was more of Germany and Japan was not
that much uh involved the way it was
during second the second world war. So
it's kind of the scenario today is kind
of like the preWorld War scenario.
Jay says greetings sir greetings to you
sir. Okay. Um no it's not a question.
Everything can be expressed
mathematically.
Disappoint equals expectations minus
reality. Anxiety equals uncertainty
times powerless.
Can you guide how we can form formulas
for everything in general? Look, I don't
know if we can have a formula or an
equation that uh succinctly and
concisely and accurately uh expresses
disappointment
or anxiety.
You are what you have put out over here
is pretty interesting. But I am not sure
if emotions are purely mathematical in
nature. Emotions are governed by very
complex
I don't know what what what should I
call it processing algorithms.
There's hormones involved. There is
neural algorithms involved. I suppose
there's I mean disappointment come can
come. It's not just one or two factors.
There can be 78 factors in
disappointment. Some of the factors will
only be understood by your subconscious
and you won't even understand them
consciously consciously. Anxiety anxiety
is is is an emotion of course, right? U
anxiety uncertainty times powerless
there is a if you're feeling anxious
anxiety obviously it's about the fear of
some unknown situation or something
that's that's impending but you can't do
thing about. So there's powerlessness
for sure, this uncertainty for sure, but
there could be other factors as well. So
I'm not sure if we can, you know,
have a mathematical equation or formula
for something as complex as emotions.
And I am not the right person to guide
you for this because I have never
attempted to do such a thing. So I lack
the experience uh for doing this. Okay.
Okay. Shushirya says, "Thoughts on
jotish/astrology? Is it scientific?" I
know not. I do not know because I have
never studied ever jotish or astrology.
I am completely ignorant
about the details of jotic or astrology.
So I I'm not the right person to ask
this. I have never studied it. So I
can't say
vidy manar says extremely worried about
bharat. Never felt so helpless. Well,
we've had worse times way way worse
times than this.
Right now, what we what many Indians are
worried about those who understand
what's happening is that we have the
light at the end of the tunnel. Keep
growing at 6 7 8% per year GDP wise for
20 years and you are a middle income
nation. That is the light at the end of
the tunnel. After a thousand years of
foreign occupation, we will finally be
at the sta the at the stage where we are
genuinely a great power.
not superpower mind you great power
because with that economic growth will
also come military growth and milit
military muscle and so on and better
standards of living and so much more and
that will precipitate reforms that could
not be precipitated earlier right
there's a tipping point that comes in at
some point so that's the light at the
end of the tunnel 20 years down the line
we're going to be somewhere where we
have not been before for the past 1,000
years but our adversaries don't want
this to happen so they are putting
immense pressure, leverage, arm twisting
on us right now. Then the next 5 years
is the break make or break time. The
next five years will determine whether
we're going to make it or whether we
were going to be broken and have another
200 years of vasalhood subjugation which
is why yeah I I can understand the worry
but uh
the worry comes from uncertainty right
that we are uncertain of the outcome but
there have been times where the outcome
was known we were under Turk occupation
for like several centuries under British
occupation for two and a half centuries
And things were so dire in those days.
It was daily genocide, wasn't it? So we
I mean imagine being ruled by ISIS for
500 years. Yeah. Many parts of India
more than 500 years. Afghanistan,
Gandhar,
literally a thousand years now.
Um, so I would say we should uh, of
course, it's it's it's a it's a it's
going to be a tough road ahead, but we
should be positive and we should all
pitch in with whatever we can
individually for the cause of the great
civilization that is ours. So let's be
optimistic.
Grant says, how do you view the Russia
Ukraine war now? Was Russia successful
in accomplishing their objectives? See
the question of was Russia successful in
accomplishing its objectives is
something we should ask when the war
ends.
We should ask this question when the war
finally ends. Whenever it ends, maybe 3
weeks, maybe 3 months, maybe 3 years,
whenever, maybe 10 years, who knows? We
don't know. We will ask this question
only when the war ends. This is not the
time to ask this question. Was Russia
successful? Russia is still involved,
engaged in the war. The war is ongoing.
What were the objectives that Russia had
in February 2022 when they launched this
special military operation?
Objectives, what were they? Number one,
the demilitarization of Ukraine. Number
two, the denazification
of Ukraine. Essentially, that was it.
And obviously, the unstated objective
was to safeguard the Russian
the the Russian majority regions of
Ukraine.
Right. So the Luhansk and Donk regions
are Russian majority overwhelmingly
Russian majority and those people live
the Russian ethnic Russian people living
in these regions were subjected to daily
bombardment and whatn not since between
2014 and 2022. That is something the
western media has never reported. So the
Russians wanted to reabsorb those
territories into Russia and that's been
achieved mostly. So that part has been
achieved. Now the Ukraine has not been
demilitarized. It has not been
denazified.
Right? So that's not happened yet. So
those objectives are still I suppose a
work in pro process. And obviously
another objective would be regime change
in Kiev.
That's also not been achieved yet. And
the long-term objective is that Ukraine
should never in the future be be in a
position where it can be used by the
West as a tool to threaten Russia. The
way the West uses Pakistan to threaten
India, that sort of thing.
So that is still going on. So it's too
early to say whether Russia has been
successful or not. But thus far it has
had partial success.
It's not fully successful at this point
in time.
Vidimar says is Iran protest two US deep
state sponsored? I think some of it is
organic. I'm sure the people of Iran
don't identify with the with the uh
government that uh I'm sure that that
all of the people of Iran don't identify
with the government that rules them, the
the the regime, right?
Many people seek democracy.
Many people seek an end to Sharia law. I
suppose
many people in Iran maybe a significant
percentage of people of the people of
Iran maybe they don't they don't want
Islamic law Islamic rule whatever
many people may want to practice a
different religion pos potentially
right so it's I would say there is a
significant element of organis
organicity or you know of or organic
behavior in the protest and that
obviously is is great for a nation that
seeks a regime you in Iran. So they can
portray their support,
they can portray their efforts to change
the regime in Thran and support for
democracy and the aspirations of the
people of Iran. So there's obviously
going to be an element of
US or Israeli involvement in this, but
there's also going to be a significant
element of of support on the ground for
a change in the regime in Thran.
Right. Protarano says looks like our
defense deals are not necessities but
just carrots to pacify and get trade
deals with other countries especially
US, France, Germany. Uh I'm not sure
what exactly you are pointing towards.
You're clearly pointing towards
something. Um
is the the I'm not sure. Something's
happened recently. There's been some
controversy. I've not looked into it.
Yeah, but yeah.
Look, um there's [snorts] always an
element of give and take.
We'll do this, you do that for us. We
want a favorable trade deal, we'll throw
in this for you. That sort of thing. So
that is something that makes sense. But
that should not happen at the at the
expense of indigenous capabilities.
So let's say we have a capa, we have a
requirement in India for 10,000
rockets of a multiarrel launch system
like the Paka or whatever. we have a
requirement for at least 10,000 let's
say and we decide to buy something
similar from another country country X
maybe 500 units so if we do that it
should not mean that we stop producing
the paka system at home right so as long
as we buy that but we don't stop the
production of the paka system at home
it's fine it's like a sweetener throw
thrown in towards a deal but if you are
buying that small number of thing and
stopping the production at home of high
quality indigenous system that's a huge
problem is that the case I'm not sure
about that.
So sometimes we have to throw in some
sweeteners to get a trade deal and that
is the name of the game. That that's
part of the rules of the game. You have
to throw in the sweetener sometimes and
that's fine. There's nothing wrong with
that as long as it doesn't affect our
indigenous
defense production manufacturing
capabilities.
Aninud Kumar says, "What can we do to
contain the US and its global
dominance?" Zero at this point in time.
Absolutely big fact. Zero.
K2340 says, "How was the UK so good at
good at plane building during the Second
World War? Spitfire. A legendary fighter
plane. The Spitfire. Outstanding fighter
plane for for its time. The 1940s. The
Mosquito. The Lancasters. The Lancasters
were bombers, right? Yeah. Can India
ever achieve this level of air
superiority with the domestic Indian
tech? Of course, we can there you need
political will. You need investment. I
mean substantial investment in the
sector. Yeah. And you need a reformation
of the education system which I will not
harp on about again because I've done I
do that in every single episode. We need
to reform the godamned Indian education
system. System which is rotten to the
core. third rate mediocre rotten
education system. We need to reform it.
We need to get rid of all the rot from
it. We need to make it merit based. We
need to make it focused laser focused on
STEM on science and technology. And we
need to make our higher education based
mainly focused on research and
development not on wrote memorization.
You do that you're going to have high
quality people coming out of the
education system who are ready to hit
the ground running in when it comes to
research and development. Right? If we
have that and we have proper investment
in these sectors, aviation,
you know, engines, jet engines and
whatnot, then we're going to have a boom
in Indian air manufacturing. So, how was
the UK so good? They had a great
education system, right? They had all
the money in the world that they had
stolen from other countries
and they had all the resources in the
world stolen from other countries.
So they had good brains. Every every
nation has good brains. We have better
brains. Of course, we are superior
intellectually from to the to the rest
of the world, I suppose. Am I being too
naughty by saying that? Whatever. So So
that was the case, right? How was
Germany so good? How was Germany so good
during the Second World War? Even the
first world war? I mean, Germany's
technological achievements dwarf that of
the UK and the US.
Germany was so far ahead of its time.
How so?
A stellar education system,
fullcale focus on industry, on
cuttingedge research and development and
industry. And when you have the
combination of these factors, you're
going to have genius level achievements.
So that's what the UK what that's what
Germany did, that's what the UK did,
that's what China is doing right now.
And we are sitting and watching them
all. And so what can we do about this?
Nothing at all sir. That's the problem.
Okay. A died in plane crash says why
haven't you talked about soldiers from
the hermit kingdom fighting for Russia
especially in Kursk as it is now
confirmed that these
not some Yakuts buryats. Am I supposed
to talk about everything in this
show? The Ask a Budget show. I answer
your questions. So my question to you is
why haven't you asked me about this
before? You ask me, I'll talk about it.
Right? This this this
show, the Ask show, the format is driven
by all of you. If you don't ask me about
something, how will I speak about it? I
need your permission to speak about it.
You ask me, I'll answer. So here we have
it. Yeah, of course there are soldiers
from North Korea who have been fighting
for Russia. Of course, they have been
fighting for Russia. We know that. So,
here we have it. I've spoken about it.
Thank you so much, sir.
All right.
Happy New Year says, "Can you explain
how can you explain how was the internet
in the 2000s? How was the speed, the
content, the apps and social media? How
did how did people
how did people look at it? How did
people think about it? what what were
people's feelings about it internet
right so I first came across the
internet in probably 9798
19979898
around that time right when I was a
student
and it was something fascinating for me
wow what is this I did not know what see
I did not know what the what it was all
about obviously when the first time you
come come across that you don't know
what it's about at that time I I did not
know how to use a computer I did not
know how to switch on or switch off a
computer, how a computer worked or
whatever. I did not know what HTML was
and so on. But then you pick it up fast,
right? So, uh how was the internet? The
speed was abysmal. Abyal. So, in India
at that time, you had something called
cyber cafes because nobody had internet
connections at home, right? That only
came in India, home internet connections
by the late 2000s. So, you had cyber
cafes where there was no coffee. It was
just a computer, a shitty old computer,
big one, big uh cubicle screen, you
know, the the cathode rate tube monitor
and that sort of thing. And it would
take 20 minutes to open up a web page
and they'll charge you like 40 rupees an
hour, which is a lot of money for that
time. Okay, so that sort of thing.
Sometimes it would take 20 minutes to to
just load a web page or something. And
everybody got email addresses. It used
to be Hotmail or something at the time.
used to be Hotmail and there was
something called Alta Vista and all
kinds of very niche websites
and uh
very interesting HTML
based websites. There was no audio,
there was no video on it. The graphics
were very minimal. It was mainly text
based. So there was the late '9s. In the
2000s you had the progression of the
internet and you had the start you had
the emergence of something called
blogging.
Blogging was the big thing, the hot
thing those days. If you were cool, if
you were up with the times, then you had
a blog and you used to blog and express
your opinions about things and so on.
And blogging apparently was pretty
lucrative for some for some people in
some parts of the world. Some people
used to make lots of money from Google
AdSense blogging and whatnot. And then
you had the start the emergence of
WordPress as a blogging platform. And
you know you could host WordPress on a
hosting provider, get your own top level
top level domain and that sort of thing.
You can do do that sort of thing. So I
also played the game. I mean I I I think
I decided to make a website somewhere in
2010. I learned how to do it. No one
taught me. Everything I' I've learned is
entirely selftaught. So then yeah, I did
all that. So the content was all niche
content, very democratic content, all
kinds of random content. Then you had
one you initially you had uh search
engines like Alt Vista and Yahoo and
whatnot but Google cracked the code.
Okay, Google gave you page rank and and
algorithmic search and whatnot and
Google that's why it became so big and
then it came up with Gmail and whatnot.
There were no apps on the internet in
the 2000s or the 1990s. Apps are a very
new thing. It was just websites you know
http
semicolon/
whatever.com it was generally then you
hadn nets andorgs that came in and today
you have all kinds of tldds right uh
social media what kind of social media
did you have you had Facebook there was
MySpace I believe I never used MySpace I
suppose I have a Facebook account lying
somewhere so it all all started with
MySpace and Facebook and then you had
Twitter coming in in the late 2000s and
Then over time you had other social
media coming. So that's kind of how it
was and things evolved to over time. Web
2.0 people used to talk about in the
early 2010s and so on so forth. Yeah.
Rajit says in the history of Bengal G
and Vanandanda was great. All right sir.
What about King Shashank?
Wasn't King Shashank great?
What about king
um Gopal? What about king Gopal? You had
so many great people in Bengal. I am not
saying that detach and vivan were not
great. Please don't get me wrong. There
are plenty of people who want to do
that. I'm saying is that the only two
people you can think of when it comes to
Bengal. There's plenty more. You have to
educate yourself for that. Of course, Na
G was one of the greatest of all. Of
course, Varandanda G was great. But have
you heard of the others?
Right.
Please, please learn about Bengal.
There's so much more to the history of
Bengal. So, it's so ancient, it's so
rich, so vast. Please learn more is all
I would say. Arya says, "Is Hindi
imposition as bad as they say or do they
make a mountain of out of a mole hill?
I'm from Assam. We learn both Asamese
and Hindi and Asame is doing fine. It
even got classical status.
Hindi imposition." Well, no matter which
language we decide is going to be the
national language of civilization
language, as long as we have this this
this this
specific form of democracy that that
thrives on creating divisions in
society, we're going to have this issue,
right? As long as as we have this system
where you get votes by creating
divisions in society, people will always
cry about imposition of this language,
that language, this language, that
language. Like you say you're from Assam
there's Hindi there's Asamese and both
and Assam is doing fine of course Assam
will doing will do fine in any state if
you have a national language and the
local language I don't think it's going
to the the the promotion of the national
language will ever come at the cost of
the local language or languages uh
Assam's got classical status well
I can think of many other languages that
deserve classical status I would say all
languages should be given classical
status. What exactly is the definition
of a classical language?
What exactly is classical dance and non
and quantum dance? Then there in physics
you have classical and clonquantum. So
which are the quantum languages
[laughter]
and which are the quantum dances I
wonder.
Yeah. So anyway, I'm I'm so glad that as
has got classical status. It's a great
language, fantastic language with such
ancient roots. But all our languages
have great ancient roots.
I would say give make all languages
classical all of them with the exception
well okay let's not get into controversy
shall we have enough of this all right
happy new year says almost all the
animals we domesticated are social
animals I think the only exception are
cats how did we domesticate them
I think it's the cats that domesticated
us [laughter]
cats are unsocial animals cats will not
hang around in big groups, right? Cats
hate big groups. I may be the one of the
only people who has seen this. When I
was a little kid,
one of the cats in our neighborhood had
given birth to a litter of I don't know,
I don't know, it's litter whatever it's
like, you know, seven kittens. Seven
kittens. And they were lucky enough to
all survive into adulthood.
And they used to hang out together. I
still remember the scene from my
childhood. Like I'm not talking about
childhood. I'm talking talking about
toddlerhood. Was a very little kid at
the time.
That's the backyard and this is the
backyard fence. Suddenly from the
backyard fence, seven cats emerge
together.
It's a seven sibling cats. Have you ever
seen seven cats going somewhere
together? I've seen that. Yeah. And one
of those cats had these spots grayish
greenish almost. Have you ever seen a
cat with greenish spots? Maybe it's
because I saw it in my childhood. Maybe
I've misinterpreted the memory as as a
cat with greenish spots, but yeah,
that's what it was.
Uh yeah. So, okay. Anyway, coming back
to what we're talking about. Are cats
social animals? They're not quite social
animals. Yeah. But, uh I think it's the
cats that domesticated us humans. Cats
don't give a damn what people say. We
don't own them. They own us. Right. And
cats are very individualistic creatures.
And maybe they are more intelligent than
dogs, but they pretend to be stupid and
they hear you fine when you talk to
them. But they only act when it it
serves their interests. If you say,
"Here's food," they'll come. If you say,
"Go and do something for me," it's going
to ignore you. So I think cats are
really intelligent animals who have
actually ended up domesticating us. It's
not us that domesticated cats. Dogs
super social creatures. Oh, dogs need
attention. Dogs need validation. Dog
dogs need [snorts] warmth and hugs and a
pack around them and so on. Horses are
also social animals. Horses hang around
in large groups of horses, right? Cows
are very social, very very emotional,
very very loving creatures. Elephants
also social animals as we know, right?
What else? Sheep are very social. Goats
social and
so on. Yeah, cats are the exception.
Cats are weird and cats Yeah. Well, they
have domesticated us actually. Okay.
Honey Sharma says, "I am confused now
between MBA or army." Well, I am not in
a position to
help you out with this because I don't
know you personally.
I don't know what your aptitudes are,
what your background is, what your
strengths, relative strengths and
weaknesses are.
I don't know. I don't know the the first
thing about you. So I can't really
without knowing you well I can't really
tell you what's better for you
personally. For some people army is a
no-brainer. You belong in the army. You
can tell. For some people you are made
for MBA. Go that. I can tell if you know
the person but without knowing you I how
can I tell you? Yeah. Right. So I I am
really sorry but I without because I
don't know you at all personally sadly I
I can't I can't tell you what's what's
best for you. You're going to have what
I would recommend is talk to elders talk
to people who are wise whose advice you
can trust and who are who have
experienced life and who know you well
and talk to multiple people like that.
Maybe mom, dad, maybe grandfather,
uncle, whoever, aunt,
whoever. Yeah.
grandma, granddad, aunt, uncle, cousins,
mom, dad. Talk to multiple people. Seek
out a range of opinions from people
whose advice is valuable and and who you
can trust and then I think that would
help you better than me randomly giving
you some some advice that that actually
makes no sense. All right, sir. Hi
Sharma, all the best. Do well, get the
right answers.
Rishi Sanmani says, "What's the root
cause of conflict between Shia Sunni?" I
don't know. I am I have not studied the
history of Islam in any significant
detail and uh yeah um there was some
kind of battle. Look, I'm not even sure
about that. So when it comes to the
history of Islam etc. I am not the right
person to ask this questions. Okay sir.
Happy new year says I think Israel is
the only country which is able to
maintain a stable fertility rate. For
the past 40 years, their fertility rate
has remained between 2.8 to 3.0. Salute
to Israel for having been able to
maintain this high TFR. Outstanding.
Good job, sir. Good job, sir. And
madams.
MK says, "Did the only good thing that
communism and socialism do in the 20th
century was challenging the West, which
is the US hedgemony like the USSR, Cuba,
Vietnam, etc."
Well, there's very
few good things that communism has given
the world.
Um, and socialism, well, socialism is a
well, another form you could say. You
know, it's along the same lines as
communism, but somewhat different.
So, is standing up to the west the only
good thing it did? I think that does not
it's not because of communism as such.
It's because of the patriotism of the
people of these nations.
See in India the communists many of them
are allegedly let's say antinationals
many of the Indian communists allegedly
serve the interests allegedly of certain
other countries allegedly whoever
allegedly pays them the allegedly
highest allegedly I think that's enough
allegedly
but in the USSR
the communist party was national
nationalistic or was patriotic the
Chinese communist did a terrible able
amount of horrific things to their
people but they looked out for the for
the interests of their nation. So and
Cuban communists again were were
patriots. So it was standing up to the
west was more about patriotism than
communism. Okay. So that is an important
distinction we need to make. Okay.
Pratana says eggs and cholesterol.
What's your opinion? Look my opinion or
my advice? My opinion should never be
taken as medical advice.
Never. Okay. Never. I am not a medical
doctor. I'm not a medical professional.
What's my opinion on eggs and
cholesterol? My opinion is you can eat
multiple eggs a day without any issue at
all. Whatever. That's my opinion which
is not medical advice. My opinion is you
can eat multiple eggs a day and you will
not have any health issues of any kind
whatsoever.
Yeah. Sometimes you could even eat eat
well I'll not throw out a number
otherwise once again my opinion is not
medical advice. I don't think eggs are
unsafe. Multiple eggs a day are not
unsafe. They are safe in my opinion.
Pratip Kumar Roy says about crown
council in the city of London. I'm not
sure about the crown council in the city
of London.
Yeah. Rishi Barat says posture check
and hydration reminder for everyone.
Thank you so so much. I will take your
reminder to heart.
Ah thank you. Thank you sir.
Um Ratib Kumar Roy says future of
Indians in Europe and America.
Future of Indians. Well, those who have
become citizens,
their descendants will continue to live
there. Eventually, they will
assimilate in some shape of I would say
not just culturally but genetically
also. Um I mean talking about I'm
talking about the next 100 200 years
future of India's next next two years, 5
years, 10 years. Um [clears throat]
they'll they'll face some issues. Yeah,
there's going to be a lot of racism
against them. uh until India becomes a
1015 trillion dollar economy when in by
which time they will be given some kind
of grudging respect I suppose.
All right. Thunderbolt says why was
Socrates forced to drink the hemlock?
Because he was very naughty I suppose.
Uh why was Socrates forced to drink the
hemlock? because uh look I don't
remember the exact exact details of the
story but it was not popular among the
the the the elite the elite of of of
Athens was it
some disagreement and they decided he he
had to be killed I don't remember the
specific details I I I last read this
like 20 25 years ago I don't remember
the details there was something that
they didn't like about him and that's
why they said you must drink this yes we
give you the the choice, honorable exit
or dishonorable exit. So he chose the
honorable exit. Do it do it yourself
itself. Okay. Raj says, "Does Hawking
radiation emit information trapped in a
black hole?" No. Hawking radiation is
purely democratic in nature. And I'm not
I'm not joking here. Hawking radiation
is black body radiation. It has a black
body spectrum. It is entirely random in
nature. So it's not emitting information
that's trapped in the black hole.
Right? A black hole, we don't know what
happens to the information. That's the
paradox, isn't it? A black hole only has
a black hole's properties can be
characterized by just three parameters.
Mass, charge, angular, momentum,
whatever else went into the into the
black hole information. I don't we don't
know. We don't quite know what happens
to it. Maybe it gets scrambled and it's
represented in some way on the horizon.
The holographic principles holographic
principle, not principles, principle. Um
and we have black holes of temperature
because yeah thermodynamics of black
holes entropy and and and and
temperature the entropy of the black
hole is proportional to its surface area
and there's a temperature and the
temperature causes the black hole to
emit radiation in the form of Hawking
radiation and this Hawking radiation has
a black body spectrum. It's entirely
random in nature. It's like a random
number generator purely and it doesn't
encode the information that is
potentially trapped in that is
definitely trapped inside a black hole
which whether it's trapped or not we
don't know but it does go inside but
does it come out we're not quite sure.
Pratip Kumar Roy says I saw somewhere a
Pakistani commented that there are no
mentions of elephants in the riga which
proves that rigidic people came from
outside.
Okay. Um I'm I'm not I've not seen what
this Pakistani person says. Uh do I know
about whether the rigida has mentions of
elephants? I am not sure. But the
absence of evidence is not the evidence
of absence. This is a basic principle in
not science, not merely science but in
just logic. The absence of evidence is
not the evidence of is not the evidence
of absence. Just because a certain
animal is not mentioned in a book
doesn't mean that this book was not
written in that country or in that land.
Come on. I mean what sort of argument is
this? What is this? I don't understand.
Yes. Come on.
Okay. Anika. Anika says, "I am worried
about India's overpopulation and what
they're going to suffer because of it.
Wish India's leaders were stronger in
the past have suffered enough.
Um, overpopulation. Yeah, overpopulation
is a big issue in India. See
historically
you know until 1947 the in in 1947 the
population of undivided India was about
330 million give or take. Yeah. And
today the population of just divided
India whatever is left after the
partitioning
that population is 1.45 four five or
something what billion which is good god
what are we doing right and this has
happened in the past 80 years I remember
when I was a kid growing up India's
population was 600,000
so sorry 600 million now I used to think
my god how big it is and today we are
more than double of that
I mean the population growth has been a
runaway population growth now India's
TFR has come below 2.1 it's about 2.0
zero maybe 1.9 sometime in the future
which means the India's population
starts decreasing
now if we keep bringing the TFR total
fertility rate down
that there's going to be a significant
and rapid
collapse of the growth rate of
population
right the population is start going to
start decreasing but collapsing TFR also
causes the rapid aging of the population
that the median age starts increasing
very rapidly And that's a disaster for
our nation. That's what China is going
through. That's what Japan is going
through even worse. So I you are right
to worry about to be concerned about
India's overpopulation because it it it
it imposes such a big strain on the
resources of the nation right so the
population does indeed need to be
brought down to the pre-artition levels
of 350 330 million or so something right
but it can't happen over the next 10
years 20 years which will require
unthinkable drastic measures it needs to
happen over the next 200 years slow
gradual decline of population otherwise
you're going to have a situation where
the average person is 60 years old 65
years old that's a disaster for a
country so you're right you're right
that India we we should we would wish
that were were better in the past
India's yeah definitely suffered enough
and so on but u we are where we are you
know one could wish that one did not
have to live in such times but all we
can do is decide what to do with the
time that we have that has been given to
us like Gandalf would say.
Okay. B Mandav says sir resigned from
government job because I didn't like it.
Now what to do? Okay. You have resigned
from a government job because you do not
like it. Now what should I do? What
should you do?
Well, you see, ideally, I would say this
is all in the past now. But ideally,
before you take some action, you should
have some plan A, plan B, plan C that
I'm going to do this. I don't like this
job, so I'm going to leave it. But
before I leave the job, I should first
determine what is my best course of
action post resignation. That's plan A.
If plan A doesn't work, what should be
my plan B? Otherwise, what should be my
plan C? That's what you should do before
you leave a job. But you have left the
job. Now, what should you do? Well, I
can perhaps answer the question if I
know you. But I don't know you, sir.
Personally, I don't know what your
background is. I don't know what your
age is. I don't know of what your skill
set is. I don't know what your aptitudes
are.
I don't know what your rel relative
strengths and weaknesses are. Uh so
without this information, I can't even
begin to tell you what you should do
now. So what I would say is the first
immediate thing you need to f do
immediately or as soon as it is possible
is to get yourself an a source of
income. Right? So get yourself a source
of income which could be a job or maybe
you have a business or whatever. Get
yourself a source of income, a stable,
reliable source of income. That's the
first thing you do. Once you have that,
you have some breathing space and then
you can decide now what should I do with
the rest of my life. Should I start a
business? Should I become entrepreneur?
Should I um take up some other job
somewhere or whatever it is right? So
the first thing I would say without
because I don't know you at all is get
yourself a stable reliable source of
income first thing and then decide what
to do with the rest of your life. All
right. So all the best. All the best
sir. We wish you the best. Fast snail
says India leading leading bricks
this year. How to maximize opportunities
opposition opportunities? India is
leading bricks this year. In what way
are we leading bricks? [snorts] Is it in
terms of economic growth? Is it in terms
of India has decided that we will be the
leader? I'm I'm not sure what you're
what you're saying. India leading bricks
this year. Let me try and Google uh what
what this could potentially mean. India
leading bricks. What is that?
Okay. India assumes bricks chairmanship
and will host the 18th Whoops. What is
this? BRICS summit in 2026. Okay. Brazil
has formally handed over the bricks
presidency to India for 2026. It's a
revolving presidency.
It's a revolving presidency. So India is
going to assume the chairmanship of
bricks this year. It's a revolving
presidency. It's not like we are the
leader of bricks. We are the nominal
chairman of bricks this year. How to
maximize opportunities?
We were the leaders along the same
lines. If you want to argue we were the
leaders of the G20 in 2023 because we
are the chairmanship of whatever of G
G20. Does it mean mean mean that we're
actually leading the G20? No.
The only leader
of the G20 is the US based on its size
and strength and all that. A nominal hat
that you wear of president for one year
that doesn't make you the leader. It
just it's it's it's a ceremonial role.
So chairmanship of bricks is a
ceremonial role. It's not a leadership.
It's not a leadership. Leadership means
you are actually the strongest in the
pack which we are not. So as chairman we
will
that's that doesn't really matter.
But Kkumar Roy says that this Pakistani
guy also wrote that the ancient Brahmans
were ancient Jews.
[laughter]
They came to India and built Brahma
temple in Pushkar in the name of Arab
Abraham.
Okay, fantastic. Jews know this. He said
Buddha and Pali are u confused. Why are
you confused?
Why are you confused? Why? This is this
is absolute nonsense.
India's civilization predates the Jewish
people by thousands of years.
Pakistanis
have this guilt. Pakistanis have this
inferiority complex because their
ancestors were forcibly converted. So
they seek to denigrate the culture and
religion of their ancestors. All
converts do this.
Why do we have to get confused by what
nonsense these people spew? Why do we
even pay attention to something a
Pakistani is saying about the religion
his ancestors were made to leave? Ignore
these people.
The MK says, "Did the US become a
superpower on a platter by exploiting
Britain's near collapse under Nazi
attack to extract its global assets and
imperial influence?" Absolutely not.
Absolutely not.
The US became a superpower by by working
on it.
How the first thing that they did was to
conquer an entire continent-sized nation
from east coast all the way to the west
coast from the Atlantic to the Pacific.
It's a gigantic land mass they conquered
by exterminating the natives and and and
and subjugating those that remained.
And then they built a gigantic
industrial capacity
and they built the ability to extract
resources, mineral resources and other
resources from the land. Then they built
a navy and a military, a massive navy,
massive military and that's what gave
them the ability to to to exploit the
collapse of Britain.
But by the time they were way more
powerful than Britain,
right? So it's not like they became a
superpower on a platter because they
exploited somebody's misfortune. No,
they built themselves up into a behemoth
which gave them the ability to finally
exploit other people's misfortunes.
Right. Okay.
S Morgan says, "I would like your views
on the type of government portrayed in
Harabot
Heinline's Starship Troopers, the book,
not the movie. If you have not read it,
I highly recommend it." This is one
science fiction movie I have not read.
Uh book I have not read. I have it
somewhere, but I haven't gotten around
to reading it. It's one of the books I
missed reading during my childhood.
I have it, but I haven't started it. And
I haven't watched the movie. I've seen
some some snippets of the movie, which
is kind of funny, but I [snorts] know
the book is a classic, an all-time
classic. It's a military classic, but I
haven't read it yet. So, I won't be able
to answer your question. I can't venture
a guess without reading it. Um, so yeah,
uh, you highly recommend it and I agree
with you and I will read it. It's a good
reminder for me to maybe pick it up my
next trip somewhere. I have a next trip
coming up very soon. So maybe I'll pick
up that book on the way on my trip if I
can find the time to read it. All right.
Run
rager says okay. R says does Starink
even need permission
they can just beam it in case of
antinational elements if the US wants
right. That's something we have to
actually explain to Indians.
But Starling doesn't have the permission
to operate in India.
Starling doesn't need permission. You
are right. Starling does not even need
permission. They can turn on the beams.
Who knows the beams are not on
right now. They will not put it on
because they want to actually get
official permission from India and make
money from Indians. I hope the
government of India denies Starlink
permission to operate in India.
Then we will see what games they play
because couple of years ago or some
something like that Starlink equipment
was found was was was
apprehended from cookie terrorists in
Manipur.
Right. So the question is is Starlink
being beamed over India's far east or
some parts of India's far east maybe the
territories that the cookie cookies have
captured where I'm not sure how much
government of India presence we have
is Starlink available there has it been
turned on over there
so Starlink to answer your question
Starlink doesn't need anybody's
permission they can just switch on the
beams
and there's nothing the government of
India can do about
Unless
unless we develop the technology
required to jam
sterling transmissions across the
subcontinent. I suppose we can do it. My
question is is the government of India
doing that? I hope we are.
Aner Kumar says what are the benefits of
India annexing and integrating Maldives
into itself and how long would it take
for India to achieve this?
20 minutes.
It would take India about 20 minutes to
annex Maldives and integrate them. But
what are the benefits?
Um what are the benefits? More power
projection capabilities, an expanded
Indian zone of influence, official zone
of sovereign influence. Uh right now
what are the drawbacks? You take over a
country like that, the Americans will
impose 3 million sanction sanctions on
you. They're just waiting for for an
excuse, the Americans, right?
So right now is not the right time to do
that. The future we'll see. I mean if if
if
uh climate change theory is true and sea
levels will rise as they say which they
could in that case we don't need to do
any things and it's a thing the Maldis
may go underwater anyway
die in plane crashes. Some US military
veterans say that Russian military is
more capable than it was before the war
even calling Ukraine war as Russia's
realtime military education.
Is Russia's military more capable than
it was in February 2022? It is. It is.
They've learned. So, like you say, this
is realtime military education. They're
having to to to to learn on the fly in
the middle of battle.
Right? They are forced to adapt on the
run.
Battle tactics are evolving every day.
It's the first time you had widescale
large scale use of drones
in warfare. And then both sides had to
come up with very rapid innovations to
to neutralize drone warfare. They're
coming up with these ugly cages on top
of tanks which look horribly ugly, but
they're effective. The drone can't hit
the tank. It'll explode a meter or two
above the tank and it's enough. It's
enough. It'll ensure that the the tank
survives. Then what about anti-personnel
drones? You can put up nets over your
trenches or whatever and the
anti-personal drones can't get through.
Just a simple net, a fishing net kind of
thing. There is that. And then there's,
you know, hypersonic weapons and all
kinds of tactics and counter tactics and
technologies that are being used now.
loitering drones, kamicazi drones,
anti-personal drones, various kinds of
mines and whatnot. All of these tactics
are evolving in real time and the whole
world is watching and I it's pretty
clear that India has learned many of the
lessons of the Ukraine war which was
very apparent during the operation
sindur uh event you know the three-day
war with aerial war with Pakistan
against Pakistan [snorts]
and uh Russia's economy has done well
it's actually grown GDP has grown and
the Russian military complex is now
Russian military industrial complex is
now churning out whatever the Russian
military needs
in in in big numbers. So I agree that
the Russian military is now more capable
than it was in February 2022 when the
war just began. Russia has this
historical tendency to not do very well
initially in any war. And then as time
goes by, it gets better and better and
better. That's what Russia has always
been like. And you can see this this has
happened once again this time in
Ukraine. So now Russ the Russian
military is battle hardened, battle
tested. It it it it it is it has learned
to counter various tactics and
strategies and the newly evolving uh new
rules of warfare and yeah it's realtime
military education. I agree.
Okay. Kajuron says lack of sunlight
sitting all day blue light cancers. Why
are we all in a race to have a life and
world that is unfit for humans and
optimized for machines? Are we advancing
toward obsolescence?
Yeah, increasingly it is so. Unless you
are engaged in some kind of uh
profession that keeps you outdoors for
long periods of time. Let's say you are
in agriculture. Uh let's say you are a
civil engineer who oversees
constructions or whatever you know
whatever else you're an athlete or
whatever. Unless you are in these
occupations, most of your time human
beings are indoors, sitting in cubicles
in offices, fluorescent lighting,
sitting 8 hours, 12 hours a day typing
away or doing something on the mouse on
the computer, you know, squinting at
very short distances which which ruins
people's uh eyes, blue light,
fluorescent lighting. Yeah. Very poor
diets, very poor lifestyles. Yeah. The
entire world is see this has this is all
the outcome
of the consequences of the industrial
age.
where humans were forced to specialize.
Humans were forced into production lines
and the production line uh
the the the the concept of the
production line was then expanded to
even software work and whatnot. So every
person is like a cog in a wheel and you
are supposed to specialize and do what
uh do do one activity over and over and
over again which is bad for your health,
mental health and whatnot. Overall it
makes people miserable. I know I've been
there at some point in my life, right?
Um
so yeah we are all going towards that a
world you know a lifestyle that's very
poor for humans. Uh we are hardly
outdoors. I don't know how many people
even look at the sky anymore. And today
if you if you're in an Indian city and
you look at the sky you see a mass of
gray. You don't even see blue skies
anymore.
If you look at the sky in the night all
you see is a haze yellow haze or
something. You hardly see stars anymore
because of light pollution and whatnot
and pollution overall.
And in India, if you live in a big city,
most people keep looking down, down,
down. People don't even look at the sky
anymore. They don't even know where the
sun rises. They don't they don't even
know that the moon has phases.
They don't even know that when you see a
star,
every day it advances
slightly ahead of where it was yesterday
at the same time. People don't see that.
People are not even aware of these
things. So it's terrible and we need a
solution for this you know. Yeah. So
you're absolutely right. These are big
big concerns for humanity.
R says only in India restaurants give
free water. Anywhere else I went uh they
always had to pay for it. Um
yeah even in East Asia now you have
restaurants. I mean if you go to a
restaurant you're supposed to pay for
water, right? In India, you'll get water
for free in most restaurants. Unless you
go to a fast food restaurant, you know,
fast food restaurant, western with a
western brand on it. In that case, you
have to pay for everything. If you're in
an airport, if you want water, you have
to pay for a little plastic bottle of
bottled water. Yeah. But in India, in
other parts of India, even in big
cities, if you go to go to Indian
restaurants, which are, you know, you
will get free water. I suppose India is
one of the few places left in the
civilized world where where you have
this. Yeah. Everywhere else you pay for
water.
Rajat says I'm flabbergasted by the
NASAta 10.19 of the Rigida that states
in the beginning there was neither
existence nor non-existence
formless void and singular. How can
anyone have known that more than that it
says that before the creation more than
that Nasadia says that before the
creation of the universe we don't know
what existed the gods came into
existence with the creation and the
formation of the universe who created
them
who created them and the creator does he
know or does he also not know it's a
profoundly agnostic
statement about the creation of the
universe. Incredibly agnostic,
incredibly skeptical.
So the Hindu view of the creation of the
universe is agnostic and skeptical. It
says even the gods
appeared with the creation of the
universe. Who created them?
Right?
So it's incredible how profound the the
the philosophy the thinking of our
ancestors all those thousands of years
ago was more profound than people who
are in existence today.
Okay. Sharon says how did a man
initially set out for a religious
pilgrimage come to be regarded as the
world's greatest traveler?
Who are you referring to, sir?
A man who initially set out for a
religious pilgrimage come to be regarded
as the world's greatest traveler? Who is
this? I seem to be at a loss. World's
greatest
traveler. Who's the world's greatest
traveler? Ibn Batuta.
Who is Yeah, we know who I is or was.
Did he set out on an expedition? Okay.
He's he went for a pilgrimage to Mecca
but journeyed for nearly 30 years
visited 44 modern countries equivalent
of that and so on. I I don't know about
the life of Iban Batuta. So can't say I
haven't studied this life so I don't
know really. I'm sorry about that. Sorry
about that.
Minimalist Maverick says how did ancient
Russians stop Turk and Arabic invasions?
The Arabs couldn't stand the cold. They
never bothered to try and invade Russia.
The Turks, the Turks also did not really
try to invade Russia. The Mongols did
and they were very successful for a
couple of centuries. The Mongol yoke
they called it. The Mongols could
withstand
any form of cold. Any form of cold. So
that's why the Mongols were able to rule
Russia for about roughly give or take
you know a couple of centuries the
Mongol yoke. And then in the Siberian
region, you had these Turk tribes, the
Tatars.
The Russians subjugated them.
Yeah. The Russians were powerful enough
to sub subjugate the Tatars. Obviously,
there was resistance for a long long
time. Omsk and Toms in those regions,
Tatar regions. And today, plenty of
Russians have Tatar ancestry.
Two former tennis grand slam champions
belong who are Russian citizens have
Tatar ancestry Marat Safin and his
sister Dinara Safhina Fatar ancestry u
so the Russians were powerful enough
they were strong enough to to subjugate
the Tatars and apart from that there
weren't really any major Turk invasions
of Russia
um R says isn't it fishing fishy that
some government supporting news channels
have suddenly started talking against
it. Um well I don't com comment about
domestic politics and these internal
matters of India so I shall desist from
commenting about this but
interesting
Sanjay Gandhi Var Munch says check had
about Alhind special obsession I don't
go into these matters I
yeah this is beyond my purview uh the
history of Islam and had all that no
that's not For me, look, I I I speak
about history, geopolitics, science. I
don't go into matters that I haven't
studied in great detail. I don't express
my opinions about it. I don't speak
about those things. So, I will not sir,
apologies for that.
Rules-based says, why can't we have a
society where every leadership rule has
two leaders, one male, one female?
Imagine two judges, two teachers, two
presidents. Dual leadership model might
be the only solution the world needs.
Why does it need the solution?
How do we know that these two leaders
are exactly the are exactly equally
qualified or exactly equally competent?
Why not have just one leader for each
role irrespective of the gender whoever
is best? Why do we need to have this
forcible duality?
I guarantee that if you bring two
leaders, one male, one female, one is
going to be slightly better.
So why don't just take that one person?
Why do we need to have this these
contrived contrived things?
What has worked for thousands of years?
Why can't we continue that?
I don't want two judges, two teachers,
two presidents, two everythings.
Why?
So I should have when I travel to some,
you know, take my next flight, I should
have two pilots and two co-pilots, one
male, one female.
Hm.
So for every uh male such tender there
should be a female such tender also. For
every fast bowler there should be a
female fast bowler.
Yeah. For every boxer there has to be a
female boxer. Look it doesn't work like
that. This is so so incredibly contrived
and artificial. We don't need that. We
just need to respect merit and
competence. Whoever is most competent
irrespective of gender, whoever is best
for a specific role should be given the
role. As simple as that. That's the kind
of society
and leadership model the world really
needs needs.
[snorts] Arun Arun says, "Was Token a
natural genius or did he plagiarize some
ideas from European mythology?"
He took a lot of ideas from European
mythology.
But that's not plagiarism.
In India, we take a lot of ideas from
the Mahabharat, from the Rama, from the
Idihas, from the Puranas and so much
more. Are we plagiarizing our our our
ancestors? No, it's part of our
heritage. We have the right to use these
ideas. Similarly, Tolken used ideas from
European mythology, from u Nordic
mythology, from Tutonic Germanic
mythology and so on. The this the this
artificial Elish language that he
invented,
most of it is taken from Nordic
languages, right? But that's not
plagiarism. He did come up with so many
original ideas and thoughts and uh the
Lord of the Rings itself, it has a lot
of these elements. But it is entirely an
original work. Right? So I would say he
was definitely a genius level writer.
If you take ideas from your own own
ancestral mythology, that's not
plagiarism. And he did modify. See,
genius is about taking things that
already exist because everything has
already been done. You take things that
don't exist that already exist and you
use them or repurpose them in in very
innovative creative ways in in which in
in in in shapes and forms that really
provide new value to those who to
society at large. That's what you're
supposed to do if you are a creator. And
he was definitely a genius level
creator. Yeah, definitely.
All right. Next. Anything Yuvie says
very intrigued like how were you in
school? Where did you grow up? And as
you said you went out for higher
education han in your formal education
background. How was I in school? When I
was in the very early school, junior KG
etc etc. I was super super super super
liked by teachers and um well
not always like okay look I I was a
pretty intelligent kid. I wasn't always
very fond of school especially the
education system the textbooks and all I
was not fond of it at all.
Um so I was an okay student.
Uh where did I grow up? I grew up all
over the place. I had a pretty
interesting
growing up experience growing up in
multiple places and all. Did I did I go
out for higher education?
Um I did not go out of the country for
higher education but I did go out for
higher education. My formal educational
background is is physics. Right. So
that's a that sort of thing. How was I
in school? I was I was
you could say I was a nerd.
You could say I was a nerd.
But the one thing that prevented me from
being a complete nerd is that I was
pretty good in some sports. Like really
good in some sports. Nobody could out
wrestle me. Nobody could lift heavier
than me. I was very strong. I was very
large. [laughter]
So that's why nobody could accuse me of
being a being a nerd. I wasn't a bully
or any such thing, you know. I was a
pretty peaceloving kid.
But yeah, so I I was pretty different
from most kids for sure. Yeah. But I
loved playing sports. I loved having fun
stuff. Yeah.
Okay. Minimalist Maverick says, "We are
100% arians. Of course, we are superior
to everybody else." Yes, sir. We are the
superior. We are Arya. And that's not a
joke. We are Arya. We are the original
Arya people. Us and the Persians. We
have to include the Persians also in
that. So us the people of the
subcontinent
all of it and our Persian neighbors we
are the original areas and if that makes
us superior to everyone else well
sure
indeed.
Uh Mitesh says what skills do mechanical
engineers need to have at the AI era?
Mechanical engineers are folks who deal
with machine tools and all that, right?
Machine tools, mechanical engineering.
You are you use machines to create
machines
and you tinker around and and yeah, it's
fascinating, beautiful, wonderful
hands-on stuff. You're making stuff
using machines. And who makes those
machines? Well, other machines make
those machines. So, what skills do you
need to have in the AI era?
mechanical engineers. Well, that's a
great question. I'm not really very very
very very very very
sure about exactly what skills you need
for mechanical engineering. Uh
mechanical engineering is all about
doing things hands-on, right? It's about
making things. Uh
you should be aware of the interface
between AI and robotics.
Okay. Um AI and robotics are going to
bleed into each other pretty soon. it's
it's already happening
and I suppose that's where something
becomes relevant for mechanical
engineers.
Um yeah I have to think about this you
know I have never given my mind or my
thought to mechanical engineering
never
but yeah the interface of AI and
robotics is definitely going to be of of
of relevance and uh of interest to
mechanical engineers so eventually it's
going to be robots that will start
building machines I suppose.
Pratip Kumar Roy says how has Bengal
Islamized and not its near by state's
history. I haven't studied this in
detail. What was the process of the
Islamization of Bengal? It obviously
happened after the Muggal era, the
Muggal Empire. Um
what was the process like? I yeah that
I'm not really 100% sure about. I'm not
100% clear about. I think a lot of the
isization happened after the British
occupation of Bengal. A lot of it, a lot
of the conversion process happened after
the British took over Bengal. They
facilitated a lot of that. Right? So a
few hundred years ago, nobody in Bengal
was uh a practitioner of the Islamic
religion. Nobody. Nobody at all.
And then the Muggal Empire I suppose
made Bengal a province of its and they
did some standard atrocities standard
Turk atrocities in Bengal but even that
did not have the effect they wanted of
widescale conversion. It's only after
the British took over that you had wild
widescale large scale conversion
but the mechanics and dynamics of that I
am not very clear about so I can I can't
really answer that in detail.
Zer Popali says has become a new member.
Well, thank you so much. Welcome to the
membership of this channel. Thank you
very much for being so kind. Welcome,
sir. Or ma'am.
Okay. Raman Balo says, "Most Mughal
Mughal architecture is just is just
Indian with a hint with a bit of a bl of
blend with Persian.
There's going to be some Persian
influences. See the muggles were Turks,
but there is no Turk culture as such. I
mean, no architectural culture as such.
The Turks originally were just were just
nomads and they absorbed culture they
absorbed religion from the Arabs. They
absorbed culture from the Turk from the
Persians right and then these muggles
ruled India
uh and um after the time of Shajahan
there's a lot of Persian influence that
they bring in
now the Persian
architectural style it's also very
similar to the Indian architectural
style also right isn't it? So most
muggle architecture is definitely mostly
Indian and there's going to be Persian
elements in it. Cal Persian calligraphic
elements, Persian styles, you know, um
you know a lot of the Persian style if
you look at the Persian paintings from
500 years ago. Okay, that time Persia
was a Turkishized
Turkey Turkish sized
nation. It was under Turk sub
subjugation. See, India was again under
Turkish sub subjugation and occupation
for several centuries. So was Persia.
So was Persia. Persia was also ruled by
Turks. And if you look at ancient
Persian paintings from 500 years ago,
you will see all their kings and other
people having those Turk eyes and Turk
facial features, not Persian facial
features.
Right? So there's a bit there's a
significant
blending
of the styles architectural and and and
uh painting and other styles of muggle
occupied India and Turic occupied
Persia. So to answer your question back
in back to what you're asking most
muggle architecture is just Indian
mainly Indian with elements of Persian
and other styles mainly Persian style
mainly Persian there's no such thing as
as Turk style of architecture and
there's no such thing as Arabic
architecture because the original Arabic
architecture is just flat squat
rectangular buildings right so it's
mainly Indian and Persian for sure
godliness says uh health alert I live in
the west and here a lot of Indian
eatables have totally different
ingredients much healthier quality and
quantity compared to the same product
sold in India. Why?
For example, a packet of chips, potato
chips of so and so brand. I will not
take brand names here because I don't
have the time for all those any
disputes. Let's say you take a brand of
chips of a major brand name whatever it
is. Let's say X.
You take a 100 gram packet of chips in
New York City and the same brand a
packet of 100 gram packet of chips in
India
and you look at the ingredients the you
know the ingredients and all you will
see that the packet in the west is going
to have way more healthy way healthier
ingredients than the one that's sold in
India. If it is let's say
let's say a bottle of jam or let's say a
bottle a packet a sache of powdered soup
whichever brand it is let's say it's
tomato soup if it's a packet in London
or New York it's going to have 5 to 10%
actual tomato
powder actual tomato powder it's going
to have way less uh artificial
ingredients and way less artificial
color coloring and so on in India
there's going to be almost nothing which
is actual tomato. It's going to have way
more artificial stuff. It's going to
have all kinds of artificial colors and
whatnot. So the Indian
packet of the same brand, same quantity
and same product essentially is going to
be a very different product. It's going
to be way more harmful to health than
the one that's sold in the west. Same
brand, same same product. So why is it
so?
If you if you take, you know, those
those chocolate spreads that you paste
onto bread and all that, whatever nut
based chocolate creams you have, without
going into the names, the Indian product
is going to be is going to have way more
refined sugar and way less good stuff.
So why is it like this?
Why? It's because they can get away with
this nonsense in India. Because the
government of India doesn't penalize
them.
Why does the government of India not
penalize them? I think we all need to
ask the government of India what the
hell are you people doing? Why are you
allowing foreign companies to get away
with these practices in India?
Why why can't you lay down the law and
lay down the rules, lay down the
specifications and the red lines? Why is
the government of India what which
minister does this come under? I really
wonder what's happening really. It's
it's terrible unacceptable actually.
Sitans Nigum has become a new member.
Sitange Nigum G very welcome a great
very warm welcome to the membership of
his channel and thank you so much for
being so kind as to take a membership.
Thank you so much.
Godliness says if NATO breaks UK, Italy
and Poland will stand with US France
will explore its own independent
pathway. And what about
Deutsland or Denmark?
Okay. So if NATO is dissolved, if the
Americans go and take Greenland, NATO
cannot continue. It simply can't
continue. So what happens?
Everybody will be made to stand with the
US whether they like it or not, whether
they desire it or not.
Trump perhaps wants to end NATO.
Perhaps it is not perhaps it is
definitely more beneficial for the US to
deal with each of these nations one to
one instead of dealing with a group of
nations in collectively.
That way the US can extract way more
from each nation. The US can impose way
more leverage
and pressure on each nation individually
in different ways than dealing with a
collective.
So if NATO breaks, all of these nations,
whether they desire it or not, whether
they like it or not, will be made to do
whatever the US wants them to do.
France is the only nation within NATO
that has a quasa independent foreign
policy. Then France will be the most
difficult to break and the US won't be
able to impose its will completely on
France.
Apart from France, every other nation
will do what the US tells them. Turkey
may have a little bit of wiggle room and
leverage because of its fantastic
geographical location. So Turkey may
have some regal, you know, some some
breathing space, some wiggle room.
France definitely has some breathing
space and some regal room. So they will
be they will bend less, but every other
nation will fully bend to whatever the
US wants them to do.
Pratib Pratep Kumar Roy says, "How to
get a software developer job with
multiple gap years?" Oh well, that's
something I've never thought about and
I've never had to think about these
things. Once I was out, I was out. I was
done. So, if you have multiple gap
years, I suppose you will have to find
some way to justify those gap years that
I was doing so and so thing, which is
fantastic. So, maybe I was doing some
research or maybe
I was doing some project for myself or
something. You have to I suppose show
something, you know, constructive.
Uh I suppose that's what you do. I'm not
really sure. I may not be the right
person, but if I was a recruiter, let's
say, let's say I start a company
tomorrow and I want to rec recruit let's
say 20 people and I look at the rums. Uh
most people have the standard rum of
ever since they started working, they
never stopped working and they have good
rums. I will hire them. If a person has
like three gap years,
then it will it will make me wonder what
was going going on with this person. So
if I am hiring an employee, I'm going to
pay them well, but I want them to work.
I don't want them to be unreliable and
disappear. Okay, I'm taking a gap year
or something that doesn't doesn't work
for me, right? So for an employer, it
makes sense to want a person who doesn't
have gap ears or if they have gapers,
they need they should have some good
genuine justification for it. So I
suppose
from your perspective you need to be
able to show good a good justification
for each of these gap years. That makes
good sense. And then you also should
have high quality skills and you should
also I suppose convince the recruiter or
recruiters of the company that you are a
reliable person. So if you are genuinely
reliable or maybe if you had some health
issue or maybe some other genuine issue
then it's understandable as long as you
have the right skills and the right
attitude even if you have gap years
which are convincing you should be able
to get a job. So that's what you need
you need to uh uh ensure that you're
able to provide.
Okay. Uh AB Chowder fanboy says a family
member of mine says Judaism is better
and converted. What is superior about
Judaism? And they think idolatry is bad.
Temples are bad in bad bad condition
etc. What is super superior about
Judaism? I don't know.
Uh I don't think Judaism is superior to
Hinduism.
If somebody feels that way, well, that's
a personal choice. Who am I to say yes
or no? It's a I think at the end of the
day, it's it's a personal matter what
religion you want to practice. If
somebody of their own valition
decides that so and so religion is best
for me then they're welcome to start
practicing that religion right but if
someone does that you don't need
justifications now to not convert into
that religion right you you do you you
do you
you need to look into these things
yourself
I don't know what is superior about
Judaism I don't think Judaism is a
superior religion to Hinduism ism. I
don't think so.
So, if you ask me what's superior about
it, I'll say I can't think of anything.
That's that's the only answer I have.
Um, Akil GK says, why am I not able to
recall events from my childhood or even
when I was in the 10th standard? But
other people are recall are able to
recall even when they were babies. Well,
I don't know.
Uh, if you ask me, I can recall things.
that go back to the time when I was less
than a year old.
I can a few things
but why can't you I I don't know ask
your parents did you have some kind of
accident did you hit your head somewhere
or did you have some kind of medical
condition that may have affected your
memory because if you can't remember
what happened in your 10th standard that
is a cause of concern I would say right
if you can't remember something that
happened when you were 3 years old well
that's kind of to some extent to be
expected everybody will have things that
happened when they were 3 years old that
they can't
But if you can't remember what happened
in the 10th standard, I think you need
to consult a medical professional,
right? You should be able to remember
the things that happened in the 10th
standard or even when you were 10 years
old. That should that that you should be
able to remember.
When it comes to events from your early
childhood, it depends on person to
person. Some people can remember things
that that happened when they were a year
old. Some people start remembering
things from the time when they were
three three years old and so on. If you
ask me, I can remember things that
happened before I was a year old.
I can and I know that it was definitely
before I was a year old cuz I remember
I'm sitting on the kitchen floor with my
bum on the floor like babies do and I've
got my cat next to me.
She was a white cat, white with patches.
And I remember this incident because she
whacked me in the face without the claws
out, claws in, but she whacked me in the
face.
very very softly but that was a shock to
me. I I saw this blue flash of light and
then when I come to she like half a
second later she's standing sitting at a
distance and looking at me and how do I
know I was less than a year old? Because
when I'm sitting on the floor with my
bum on the on the floor, my cat is
sitting next to me, half sitting, half
standing, her bum on the floor, her
front legs out like that and her face is
at the same level or slightly higher
than mine, which means I was smaller
than a cat at the time. So the point is
I can remember things that happened when
I was less than a year old. If you can't
remember something that happened in the
10th standard, I think you need to
consult a proper medical professional
and look into your personal history.
what happened that has caused this this
kind of condition that probably is a
cause for concern and you should look
into this very seriously and at as early
as possible.
Uh so so all the best Akil all the best
please do this at the earliest.
Om says if Iran falls then is it
possible that the US might feel that
Israel is too free and that and has US
has no leverage left on Israel?
Netanyahu is already thinking of getting
free from US support. Will US reconsider
things? What's my opinion? No matter
what happens, the US will not stop
supporting Israel. That is my opinion.
The US will not stop supporting Israel
even if Iran falls. Yeah, I don't think
so. Why do I not think so?
Because too many high level American
politicians
support Israel.
That's why.
Uh, a lot of it's it's no secret, it's
no conspiracy theory that a lot of uh
high ranking American politicians are
have Jewish ancestry.
And look, if you have Jewish ancestry,
you're going to support the Jewish
homeland. What's wrong with that? So in
the west you can have dual citizenship.
You can have this thing and then the US
and Israel are are unconditional allies.
The US gives unconditional support to to
Israel. And I think that even if Iran
falls whenever it falls or if it falls
the Americans will not ever stop
supporting Israel. The US will not
reconsider things. Certain presidents
may be less favorably inclined towards
Israel. the US support I don't see it
ending if uh or or being reconsidered if
Iran falls
died in plane crash says this platform
is censoring my super chats well I'm
sorry to hear that I'm sorry to hear
that I don't know what it is about or
you know maybe sometimes it's some words
that that trigger the sensor maybe it's
it is sometimes some sentiments that
trigger the sensor I am not sure what
exactly it could be but Um well
yeah no surprise
says thoughts on latest scramjet test
crossing 12 minutes. Let me see. I'm not
aware of this. Let me see. Scramjet
test.
Okay.
What do we have? Press Information
Bureau of India. Dr. What kind of a
website? Can't they make a better
website? These people.
How do I get rid of this nonsense? Okay,
let us say, can we inspect this thing?
Okay, let's inspect this. And where's
this element? This this one here. Let's
delete that. Kaboom. That's how we can
do it. So, DRDO conduct and this is from
the 9th of January 2026, which is 2 days
ago. DRDO conduct successful ground test
of full scale actively cooled long
duration scramjet engine for hypersonic
missile program and achieving a runtime
of over 12 minutes at the scramjet
connect pipe test facility on January 9
and this was a full scale
[clears throat]
actively com cooled long duration
standard engine so it was not a scaled
down model this was a fullscale model
and this achievement builds upon the
earlier subscale test in 2025 April for
long duration. This is a massive
advancement.
Okay.
And this this technology has the it's
capable of exceeding Mac 5 for extended
periods. This is incredible. It's got a
cutting edge air breathing engine which
obviously it is a utilizes supersonic
combustion to m to sustain longduration
flight.
So we have successfully validated the
design of an advanced scramjet combuster
as well as the capabilities of
state-of-the-art test facility.
This is a major milestone.
I would like to congratulate very
heartily uh the government of India and
all the engineers involved in this
matter. Outstanding, brilliant. This is
a breakthrough technology. This is a
quantum leap in technology. Outstanding.
This makes India very dangerous once we
operationalize this in the battlefield.
So now we have a full scale scramjet
engine that has
you know achieved combustion full scale
supersonic combustion that exceeds 12
minutes in duration. Now what you do is
you integrate that with the missile and
test it out and then you do multiple
tests and you iteratively tweak the
design to make it even better and in a
year or two you can have that on actual
missiles and what I don't know what what
name we will give to the missile but
it's going to have to be a very very
aggressive name okay so yeah this is
outstanding outstanding brilliant all
right Sharma says I wish to travel the
world and eat a sh and and earn a
ton of money that's MBA but I also have
interest in weapons and all tactical
things. Army will give fearlessness for
life but MBA will give money in the
short term. MBA will give money in the
long term as well. So look, you want to
travel the world, you want to earn a
ton of money. you
well you can do that if you have an MBA
I suppose and you know MBAs generally
earn a lot of money in the travel I
suppose if you're in the right industry
and MBAs can go into any industry
essentially
but you also have interest in weapons
and tactical things and army will so I
suppose you can do an MBA but also learn
some martial arts at the same time and
maybe you can do an MBA and enter a
company that designs weapons or
something you can always mix and match
things you know so I I think look
fearlessness, army, all that is great
but so you you to ask yourself which is
your overriding desire. Is it to do
weapons and go into the army and be
fearless? Is that what is is is is the
primary desire in your life or is the
primary desire in your life to travel
and earn a lot of money? decide what
what what is the first primary
overriding desire and then make that
your career and make the other thing the
second thing your hobby or whatever or
or or your secondary thing. So even if
you're in the army you can retire early
I suppose and then leverage your army
skills and experiences into business and
so on. So yeah
so yeah that that's what I would say all
the best. Hanisha H S4 says, "Good
evening, sir." Good evening. I'm doing
well. I hope you're doing well as well.
How to build better habits and be a
polymath. You're my role model. I want
to be like you, sir. Okay. Uh I don't
know how to be a polymath. I can only be
myself. And if being myself is what you
regard or other people regard as a
polymath, well, well, I suppose
I I look I never at any point in my life
decided that I'm going to be a polymath.
um for the longest time I'm sure I did
not even know this this word polymath
existed right um re R renaissance man
polymath these words I learned probably
in my 20s before that I was not aware of
this
um so how to be a polymath I look don't
try to be a polymath don't try to be
this person that person just be yourself
ask yourself what are the things that
interest me what are the things that
fascinate me and go and learn go and
study those things, right? That's that's
what we should do. Don't try to emulate
so and so person even if uh that person
inspires you,
right? Uh
try to be the best version of yourself.
So what every person actually needs to
do is to first understand who you are.
How do you do that? You have to spend
time by yourself,
a long amount of time by yourself
regularly and think about yourself.
Think about go back to your childhood.
What are the things that you enjoyed?
What are the things that made you happy
when you were a child when you were 3
years old? What made you happy? What
were your hopes, dreams, ambitions,
aspirations when you were three? What
did you fantasize about when you were
three? Those things indic are indicators
of who you tr truly are because later in
life we are inundated with other
people's opinions and experiences and
what not and that kind of becomes layers
on top of who we really are. So
understand who you are, understand what
things interest you go and learn them in
the most uh
the most in disciplined way possible if
if required just learn whatever and uh
that's how you can be your version of a
polymth. How to build better better
habits.
Habits are systems. Yeah.
So then make a list of people you
admire. Top five.
And try and study how
they have become successful at whatever
they do and what kind of habits they
have and then try to reverse engineer
that in the context of what you want to
achieve. Right? And that's how you build
better habits. The point is don't try to
build 27 habits at the same time. I want
start with one habit only. Okay, let's
say I want to start waking up at 5:00
a.m. every morning. Then I want to start
exercising. Then then I want to start
eating in a certain way. Have a certain
kind of diet. Then I want to be able to
study these many hours a day. This and
that and this and that. You can't do all
at the same time. Start with just one
thing. Make that a habit first. First
first two three months. Then stack
another habit on top of that and make
that a pattern for three months and not
that way. So habits have to be built
over time and slowly slowly slowly. You
can't do too much at the same time. too
many changes at the same time right so
that's how we do it all right sir all
the best harsh
godliness says TFR of India is about 2.1
just in border but the most dangerous
part is Hindu TFR in India is now 1.9 in
comparison of 2.6 ics of so and so and
also what will the what will be the
actual TFR of um listen I will not go
into Hindu Muslim Hindu Muslim things I
I stay away from this matter
I I I don't comment about Hindu Muslim
matters okay illegals should not be in
India I'm very clear about that no
matter what their religion is if they
have come illegally out
if you have broken India's laws it means
you are a criminal if you enter India
illegally you are breaking India's laws
which means you are a criminal a foreign
criminal criminal. Such people need to
be deported immediately.
That's what I'm clear about. It it has
nothing to do with religion. It's just
that they are criminals. They are
illegals. Apart from that, I will not
comment about Hindu Muslim issues. I
never do that and I want. All right,
sir.
Humanity survives. Thank you very much.
Humanity survives. I hope humanity does
survive indeed. Thank you so much, sir.
Or ma'am, thank you.
[clears throat] Deep learner says, "Is
it possible for Russia to push a secular
candidate of their own who favors
democracy to counter Sha's monarchy to
topple the Islamic regime?" No.
To make a long story short, Russia can't
do that. Secular candidate of Russia.
No, there's no such thing. There's no
such candidate.
It's not going to going to be possible
for Russia at all to do that. The only
candidate right now that's viable as an
alternative to the Islamic regime is the
US propped the US supported shah the son
of the shah the son of Muhammad Raza.
Yeah. Who? Yeah. Whatever. So there is
no other candidate that I can think of
and who would be you know so the son of
the sha as the pedigree of his father
that his father was once the the puppet
sha of Iran and that's why people have
hope because of the lineage apart from
that there's no other candidate one can
think of so it's not going to be
possible for Russia to do do any such
thing it won't be
humanity survive says who was the
vehicle of Indra from the vedasawat
The elephant, the white elephant, wasn't
he?
Right.
The elephant's name was Aravat, was it?
Let me see.
Aravat.
Uh, yeah. Multi-headed white elephant in
Hindu mythology. The mount or the
vehicle of Lord Indra. That's right.
That's the vehicle of Lord Indra. And
there's a city named after Indra.
Indrauri.
It's Bangkok. Bangkok is Indrauri.
Okay.
Zach Zam says, "So speculation that the
Indis Valley civilization disappearance
was due to lost trade due to Bronze Age
collapse in the Mediterranean. Anything
to it?" So we had the Bronze Age
collapse in the Mediterranean. Which
year was that? 2077
2177. Which year was that roughly? Uh
Bronze Age collapse. Which year was
okay? It was 11
12th century BC. 12th century BC. So if
we have the late Bronze Age collapse in
the Mediterranean region, Eastern
Mediterranean uh in the 12th century BC,
1127, 11th 12th century BC.
And some people will speculate that the
disappearance of this Indis Valley
civilization was because of because of
something connected to this because they
they lost the trade revenue that they
had with the Mediterranean. That's why
the entire civilization collapsed
because that's the only source of
revenue that they had. This is gone. We
can't survive anymore. So we all
collapse. Back of cards. Fascinating
argument is it first? So we are taught
okay that there used to be in the west
of India, northern and western India all
those thousands of years ago this
mysterious civilization
the Indas Valley civilization that
existed several thousand thousand years
ago and then one day mysteriously
disappeared.
Perhaps there was a large scale invasion
by aliens from Mars who abducted
everybody like the Americans abducted
Maduro. They took everybody away. They
all disappeared and then the cities fell
into dis disrepair and became lost for
thousands of years. That's what we are
taught. You know something like that we
are taught. We are taught that this
civilization mysteriously dis
disappeared and we don't know who the
people were.
The fact is that these people were our
ancestors and this was one phase of our
history of Indian history of the history
of India's civilization. It's the
Saraspati phase or the Saraspati Hindu
phase of our history. Okay. Why did this
these population centers
disperse over time? Why were the cities
abandoned? Because of climate change. So
the Bronze Age collapse also could have
been caused by among multiple factors
climate change. Maybe there was this
massive super elino kind of event,
drought, massive drought for 50 years or
something which could have caused the
bronze age collapse in addition to
invasion by the sea peoples and whatn
not and the same pattern could have
happened minus the sea peoples in
northern western India el nino drought
and all that. So 6,000 BC something
happens in India. The Indian rainy
season starts declining monotonically
slowly very slowly very gradually over
time. 6,000 BC the intensity of the
rainy season starts declining
and the great river Saraspati which used
to flow from the Himalayas to the sea uh
to the Indian Ocean western Indian Ocean
so-called Arabian Sea Sea of Sabarashtra
that river starts declining in size used
to be a massive river way greater than
the Sundu river slowly starts declining
and from 6,000 BC to 2000 BC the river
by 2000 BC the the southern half of its
course it's dried out the Saraspati
If this great river dries out and the
other rivers also decline because of the
decline in the in the monsoon, then all
the great cities built in this region,
they can't sustain their large
populations.
So the people start migrating away
slowly over 500 or 1,000 years, not one
day to the other, it's gone. It was a
slow gradual decline
and most of the people of this region
went eastwards around 2,000 BC 1500 BC
eastwards and settled in the Ganga,
Yamuna, Nmada etc. Plains, valleys and
this was the beginning of the
Mahajanapad era of India
and some of these people went westwards
outside the subcontinent. They migrated
all the way to Anatolia etc where they
founded the Hittite and Mitani empires.
They've went to West Asia and they
brought cattle with them. Indian Zebu
cattle first ever introgression into
West Asia is around this time,
right? So it's all interconnected. It
has nothing to do with the trade loss
due to the Bronze Age collapse in the
Mediterranean. Nothing like that. But
yeah, our historians and foreign
historians have to invent wild
speculative ideas to explain the
mysterious disappearance of the
civilization. It never disappeared. We
are a continuation of that civilization.
It is our civilization.
Okay. R says only area where India acts
as a superpower is cricket. If India
were to act as a superpower in cricket,
it would get Pakistan banned from
cricket. We don't do that.
Disappointing.
Ammon Kumar Dhankar says if the universe
is expanding our data collection
instruments must also be expanding. We
should also be expanding. Am I
am I
am I?
So doesn't it have any effect to be
[laughter] considered
is my
uh arc.
[laughter]
Okay. Okay. Okay. So if the universe is
expanding, shouldn't everything be
expanding? Shouldn't our instruments
also be expanding?
Shouldn't we consider this effect? Are
these calculations credible?
Okay. See, the universe is expanding and
we have evidence of the expansion of the
universe. Now what sort of expansion is
happening? The universe is expanding at
the largest scales
not at the small scales. If it was
expanding at the small scales also then
the distance between the earth and the
sun would also be increasing. The
distance between the earth and the moon
would also be increasing. The distance
between two atoms would also be
increasing
but it's not expanding on the small
scales.
Our closest galaxy is Andromeda about
2.5 million light years away. This
galaxy Andromeda is getting closer to
us. In a couple I don't know when in a
few billion years the Milky Way and the
Andromeda galaxy are going to collide.
They're going to merge together and
create and form a vast combined galaxy.
So the expansion of the universe is not
affecting the gravitational attraction
between the Milky Way and Andromeda.
These two are coming together. They are
the collapse is going to happen. The the
the the the merge is going to happen in
a you know in a couple of billion years
or so. Right? So the expansion of the
universe is happening at larger scales
than intergalactic scales like Milky Way
andromeda. It's happening on the largest
scales in the in the universe and the
expansion is very very very minimal. It
is only visible and measurable at the
largest scales. At the small scales,
gravity overcomes this attract this this
the attraction of gravity overcomes the
expansion of the universe.
So the calculations are absolutely
credible. Okay, absolutely credible. We
know this is happening because we can
see that the galaxies far away are
redshifted.
They're redshifted which means that they
are moving further away from us and the
further a galaxy is the more redshifted
it is which means that the expansion is
accelerating at the largest scales.
Okay. So that's how it is. It's not
affecting space locally. It's not
affecting space at the scale of like a
few million light years. It's only at
vast scales that the acceleration that
the expansion is is is overcoming the
attraction of gravity.
Okay. Stonel Mishra says what's the
celudian hypothesis?
What is the celudian hypothesis?
Um we know that the earth's crust is
ever changing. This erosion due to wind
activity. There's erosion because of the
effect of sand carried by wind over
millions of years. There's erosion
because of water, the activity of water,
the action of water on the surface of
the earth. And then there's tectonic
activity because of which parts of the
earth earth's crust go under other parts
of the earth earth's crust, right?
Tectonic plates always the subduction
and all that of the tectonic plates. The
cumulative effect of all of this is that
every few million years maybe every few
hundred million years
the entire surface of the planet is
unrecognizable.
Much of the earth's crust over time over
millions of years gets pulled under the
surface of the of the earth and sucked
into the magma layer. it it melts
and as such because of all these factors
because the earth's surface is ever
changing
because of this if you had a
civilization that let's say existed on
our planet 500 million years ago it's
very likely we will never find any trace
of it.
So what if there was a race of
ancient beings who were who existed on
our planet let's say 500 million years
ago or a billion years ago let's call
them hypothetically the celudian race
what if there was an advanced
civilization just as advanced as homo
sapiens a billion years ago will we find
evidence of them today the answer is
mostly no so that's just a thought
experiment
it's a thought experiment it doesn't
mean this actually ex happened you know
but if it happened we wouldn't know
about it so that's kind of the idea
behind the celian hypothesis
pascar Gupta says we need Indian github
before anything do you think open source
platforms like linux are also
infiltrated by the CIA because we v
Windows is 100% compromised
um I don't think that's anything that's
[clears throat] not compromised
anything that comes from the west is
compromised by the test there's back
doors there's loopholes there is all
kinds of stuff that's built in
if it's something that comes from China
the same story once again so eventually
every country will have to build build
its own systems yeah I don't think even
open source platforms are entirely safe
so I I agree with you we need this
ammon says please invite Mr. Mr. Vikam
Sud on the podcast. We'd love to see
that. Okay, good suggestion. That's a
very
well very distinguished and very
[snorts] accomplished gentleman. Thank
you for the suggestion. I will consider
it very seriously. Maybe let's do that.
All right. Thank you. [clears throat]
Khan Gupta says, "Free will or
determinism? Was Einstein a
determinist?" I'm not sure about whether
Einstein was a determinist or not. Free
will or determinism? I am not very sure.
Uh look most likely it's super
determinism most likely if you look at
what we know about physics.
So we know that the un the best theory
that we have based on all the best
evidence observational and empirical
evidence we have the best theory is the
big bang theory the standard model of
physics
in this what do we have built in
essentially everything is differential
equations
right you had a set of initial
conditions at time essentially t equal
to0 the moment of the big bang expansion
of spaceime and everything within it and
then every particle Every quantum of
energy everything its fate is determined
essentially by differential equations
which are just just mathematical in
nature and there is a element of
randomness built into it because of
quantum fluctuations right but that that
randomness is genuinely random.
So beyond that randomness, everything
else is just essentially predetermined.
But the element of randomness throws in
um you know a dark horse into the
situation.
But does it mean that we have free will?
The randomness doesn't give you free
will. The randomness just creates some
some amount of chaos in the universe.
So based on what we know, it looks like
it's all super determinism and
everything is predetermined. What I am
saying right now was determined because
of the initial conditions in the big
bang. That is actually more likely than
not.
Ankita Kasabji. Anka G. Good evening
ma'am. Good to see you. Uh Iran at the
verge of collapse and imminent regime
change. Who is going to replace current
government? According to you, Mr. Raabhi
coming to power is better or worse for
Iran? Looks like Iran Iranis are eager
to be vasalized. What's my opinion?
See, let me give you this example.
Bengal
was under Turk rule for a long time,
right? This this fellow Siraju Dullah,
he was brutal. He was barbaric. He was
super oppressive
towards the people of Bengal.
So when Robert Clive defeated
Sirajadalah,
the people of Bengal were like, "Oh my
god, we are saved. Robert Clive, you are
our great savior." Was it Robert Clive
who defeated Suraj Dullah? Let's see.
Okay. Did Robert Clive defeat
defeated grammar? Come on. Yeah, Robert
Clive defeated Siraj Dullah. That's
right. Plus C. So when Robert Clive
defeated Surajullah, the Bengali people
after all this all these years of
operation they felt liberated and they
welcomed Robert Clive with open arms as
a liberator.
Little did they know he would end up
being worse than anything they had
imagined and worse than Siraj Dullah.
Could you blame the people of Bengal for
that? No.
When Alexander the Greek marched into
Egypt
which was then a vasal of the Persian
aimed Empire, the Egyptians welcomed
Alexander as a liberator.
Little did they know Alexander would
further vaselize them even worse.
So you see when you have the situation
in Iran today where the people are
laboring under what they perceive as the
oppression of the regime of the ayatas
they're tired of those those rules they
are tired of the Islamic law let's say
and whatever else they want freedom
democracy
in that case they may see Mr. Razaphi as
a great savior.
Many of them the young people would not
be would would be tired of they may
perhaps regard what they have been
taught by the ayatas that Muhammad Ravi
was a US wasal. They may have they may
think that this is propaganda designed
to mislead us right because they don't
like the theatas that sort of thing. So
so maybe the people of Iran are just
tired of the of this regime and they
want to be liberated. They want freedom.
They want human rights. They want
democracy and they are not quite aware
that in the shape of human rights and
democracy which is this big Trojan horse
going to have vasalization.
So that is genuinely a possible
situation when it comes to Iran. Um but
if there is a regime regime change in
Iran most likely 99.9% it will be uh the
son of the sha the current Mr.
who will be the new leader of Iran, the
new Sha or whatever you want to call it.
The the Americans may may ask Iran to
have an election and then they will
elect this guy and that's going to start
a new a phase of vasalization of Iran.
Yeah.
Okay. Amay Deshmuk says, "Do you do we
have free will as physics doesn't
allow?" Look, we don't know for sure,
but as far as physics is concerned,
probably we don't have free will.
probably the universe is super
deterministic in nature most likely if
if what we know about physics is correct
but um does it mean that's the case?
Look, physics science
can't really explain much of the
universe for us. Whatever the best
theory we have, the back big bang
theory, the the standard model of
physics, it can explain about 4% of the
universe and that too not very well. 96%
of the universe it can't explain at all.
So we we are a long way away from
understanding the universe. Believe me,
we are a long way away. Ani Rud Kumar
says what's the future of democratic
India for the next 100 years? Will we
retain this democracy or shift to a
monarchy or split up against into
smaller nations? We have no idea
whatsoever. I am not Nostra Damus. I
don't know what's going to happen in the
future. I wish I could but I can't. I
don't know. All I can say the next 5
years are going to be a period of time
that will either make India or break
India. If India is able to survive the
next 5 years as a sovereign nation
without bending to the will of more
powerful nations, then India will
essentially become unstoppable
and keep growing until it reaches its
maximum destiny. Otherwise, India will
become basalized for the next god knows
how many years. I don't know about the
future of democratic or undemocratic
India. But I I can tell you the next
five years are the make or break time
for India. And democracy or not, I don't
care. I don't care what system of
government is it is as long as it is
beneficial for the people and the
civilization. I don't care whether the
cat is black or white as long as it
catches mice. Okay. Okay.
Uh Gajjapati Dv says how sending aloo
piaas diesel dal mut chana tomat
electricity to Bangladesh is helping
India while Hindus are being attacked
and alive there daily what are we
missing missing here I'm not quite sure
electricity to some some extent it makes
sense we are supplying a significant
amount of Bangladesh Bangladesh's
electricity the group is supplying this
electricity Bangladesh I believe is
refusing to pay or whatever but this
gives us leverage over Bangladesh if we
stop it Bangladesh goes you know
substantial portion of Bangladesh goes
without power and they have no way to
replace that. So that gives us leverage
over Bangladesh. I don't know about
Alupia's tomato diesel whatn not giving
that to Bangladesh I'm not sure how
selling that to Bangladesh helps India
while Hindus are being unalived there
I'm not sure how it helps India but I
don't know yeah I I don't have the
answer to that how it helps India
okay Jay says sorry for the question
equation I read that in the book uh
which equation where you are trying to
create equations about uh emotions and
all look you don't have to be sorry for
that I I don't know how to do that and I
have never studied that I've never tried
to do that. It doesn't mean that you
have to be sorry for it. Please don't
ever be sorry for thinking and trying
new things. Try new things. Try things
nobody has tried before. Okay? Do it.
Don't allow someone's criticism or
someone's perceived criticism
detract you from from trying new things.
Don't ever do that. Try different
things. If you read something from a
book, try it.
Okay? Follow your curiosity. How do you
care what someone's opinion is? You do
what what you feel is interesting.
Follow your curiosity. Don't be sorry.
Don't ever be sorry. Okay. All the best.
Do well.
Rajat says, "What is the future of
physics?"
Standard model, dark standard model,
dark matter, quantum gravity.
Um, what's the future of physics? Well,
if you were to ask me what I would what
I want answers to, I want answers to
dark matter and quantum gravity.
No, first of all, I want answers to dark
matter and dark energy.
Dark matter is it merely
an artifact of the equations? If we have
modified gravity,
if we modify the equations of gravity,
if we combine, if we have modified
Newtonian dynamics, does that resolve
the question of dark matter?
or is it actually some class of
particles that we
that that
interact purely gravitationally? So
that's one question. Dark dark energy,
we don't even can't even begin to
understand what that is. Is it
quintessence? Is it something else?
That's another question. Yeah. Uh
quantum gravity. Yeah, it would be nice
if we can reconcile quantum mechanics
with gravity because [laughter]
uh we all try that.
What's the future? I don't know what's
the future. Right now, we are we are
stuck. We are stuck. All of us are are
stuck. And the string theory has held us
back for 50 years. We have hit a brick
wall. We don't know how to go through
it. Um the big question out there, the
first question we have to resolve is is
gravity. What on earth is gravity? We
need to make a breakthrough in gravity.
A 100 years since 1915, we have we are
following the same equations, the
Einstein field equations. There has to
be a better there has to be an
improvement over this because the
ancient field equations obviously run
into problems at the center of certain
objects called black holes right the
equations blows up they blow up and
throw up infinities infinities are not
actual infinities they are a symptom of
an issue that the equation fails there
so it clearly is telling us we need an
improvement to Einstein's field
equations but uh where is that so yeah
maybe that's the future
Okay,
I am Koshik says, "If God created us,
what's the purpose of these galaxies,
black holes, etal particles are we made
of and where is it getting energy?"
So
maybe there's there was there's a
creator. Maybe there's a creator. Okay,
the creator has a very powerful computer
bigger than this universe. And this
creator has coded
the physics of the game
game physics coded
and then created a simulation in which
we are living. So what's the purpose? We
don't know the purpose why we have all
of this. The creator has decided if
there's a creator.
The maybe the creator is a programmer
who is living in a hyper universe beyond
what beyond our universe and our
universe is actually inside. It's a
simulation inside a large hypercomput
and maybe the creator is running a
simulation to learn something or maybe
for his or her or its entertainment.
So look when we talk about god
we we go beyond logic right a god or
gods I don't know what goes on in their
minds right we are just mere humans.
So a creator is like a programmer who
has decided for whatever reason to
create a game with a specific set of
rules that only he or she knows and why
did they do it? Well, we have to ask
them. We can't answer that. See?
[laughter]
Okay. Okay. R says if why does
Usbakistan love India? All Indian
travelers online says Usbakistan treats
them with love if they are Indians.
I haven't been to Usbakistan. I'm not
quite sure. I don't know. But I am I'm
I'm not opposed to this. I welcome this
very much. Thank you Usbakistan for if
you are being so nice to Indians. Maybe
I should visit soon I I don't know maybe
I'll go and find out. How about that?
Yeah. H very interesting.
Okay.
Chanaka. Thank you very much Chanaki G.
Thank you so much. Appreciate it. Um
Firefly says still hopeful for MMA given
given how boring 2025 was.
Oh, mixed martial arts. I haven't really
kept up with mixed martial arts the last
year. Kamzad, what was Kamzad up to?
What was that last fight? That was the
most, how to put it politely, the most
boring fight you can ever imagine. And
he retained his title and all. I I'm not
sure what really happened in 2025.
MMA obviously it's a more exciting sport
than just wrestling or just boxing
because you have all the elements put
together.
Um, it depends on the fighters. It
depends on the rules and all that. I'm
still hopeful for MMA. Yeah, we need
exciting champions. That's what we need.
So, we have Connor is still around, is
he? I don't know what he's doing. Uh,
it's kind of boring, a little boring
without Francis Inanu.
Khabib has retired. So, yeah, we need
some new exciting champions or or
fighters that will make things
interesting. Yeah,
Hersh S4 is a new member. Thank you so
much, H S4. Welcome to the membership.
Thank you very much.
Okay. Raguir Singh says, "Are the
protests in Iran due to foreign powers
or people are just fed up of moolas if
regime changes? Is it 100% that the new
leader will be pro- US any good hopes?"
First question, are the protests in
India in Iran due to foreign powers or
are the people just fed up of the
moolas?
The people I would say a lot of the
people are tired of the moolas. A lot of
the people
are tired of the laws, the Islamic
regime, the Islamic laws and all that. A
lot of people people are most likely
genuinely tired of this.
And that is a condition that foreign
powers will rush in to exploit
and they will obviously put some fire
onto the fuel.
So I think the protests in Iran are due
to a combination of two factors. One,
the people are genuinely fed up. Second,
foreign support in some shape or form,
covertly.
Okay. Now, if the regime changes, is it
100% likely that the new leader will be
pro- US? 99.9%
pro- US- leader. 99.9%. The son of the
former Sha. Yeah, most likely that guy.
Subish Na says the young people around
across the world are getting addicted to
social media a lot including the US and
as you said sir continued
and US is on the verge of becoming a
hyperpower nation by the time these
genz's will be their leaders what will
they potentially to
what will they potentially
potentially where's the continuation I'm
looking for the continuation
what will they potentially
Give me a second. Let me find it. Huh?
What will they potentially do to keep
these future kids
mentally strong and make them think big
unlike today's visible leaders and the
deep state leaders so that the US
maintains its global hygemony unlike
Indian leaders who don't?
What will the US do to keep these future
kids mentally strong? Look, in any
cohort of of kids, let's say Gen Z are
addicted to social media, okay? And
let's say Gen Z is uh let's say 50
million in the US. Hypothetical number
I'm throwing out just for the sake of
the argument.
So let's say Gen Z is hypothetically 50
million in population in the US and
overall
Gen Z is addicted to social media. It
doesn't mean that every Gen Z person is
going to be addicted to social media.
Even if 5% aren't addicted to social
media, that's two and a half million
people right there. That's a big chunk
of the population.
And
some of them can be very viable leaders,
right? So you will always find
highquality people in any group in any
population group, right? Um and when it
comes to the elites, they will ensure
that their kids are not addicted to
social media, right? they will set
different rules for their own kids and
so on. So yeah that's how it goes. So
even if overall Jenz is addicted to
social media most of them there will be
some genzi who are high quality who are
not addicted to social media who have
been trained properly or who have
decided to be different and who have
higher standards and so on. Uh, and
that's how and I'm sure that that that
that that the elite, the American elite
people, you know, they will train their
own kids differently
and that's how they will maintain their
global hedgemony.
So, I'm sure they've got a proper plan
laid out for these matters.
Okay.
Right. Um,
Kiki Sashan says, "Thank you, sir. It
means a lot." Uh, well, you're very
welcome. Have you asked a question? I'm
not sure if I've taken it. But uh thank
you very much. Your support just not
you. You Susant and everybody else all
of you my viewers your support your your
questions your your viewership all of
that that matters a lot to me. That
means a lot to me as well. I am very
privileged to have all of you as my
viewers. So thank you all. Thank you to
all of you. Thank you very much indeed.
Emerald meets Ouburn. Emerald meets
Auburn. Well, that's quite a
combination.
That's eyes meet hair, is it? Okay.
[laughter] Emerald meets Auburn says,
"Final year engineering undergrads
shifting to applied quantum physics with
ISRO and overseas research. I may have
admits abroad and an ISRO job option. My
field isn't strong in India yet. Go
abroad or take ISRO. despite the
trade-off.
Okay. Final year engineering graduate
undergraduate you're moving shifting to
applied quantum physics with ISO and
overseas research. You may have admits
abroad. You also may you have an ISRO
job option but your field isn't strong
in India yet. So maybe next 10 years you
may not have good job opportunities.
So should you go abroad or take ISRO
despite the trade-off? You're a young
person. You're starting off. You have
two options. One is foreign admits. One
is an ISRO job option. The salary will
be less like significantly less. ISRO
doesn't pay well. And your field applied
quantum physics applied quantum
mechanics isn't strong in India yet.
That's the field of your interest. ISRO
is about rocket scing.
It's about aerodynamics. It's about you
know space aeronautics and rocket
engineering, rocket propulsion so on.
It's not about applied quantum physics.
Yeah. So what should you do?
I always
I always recommend to young people the
first 20 years of your adult life focus
on yourself and on maximizing um your
growth opportunities and the experience
you can gain the first 20 years at least
of your adult life. So let's say your
adult life starts at 20 until at least
the age of 40. Be selfish and focus on
yourself.
Gain as much experience as you can make
as much money as you can. Acquire as
much skills as you can. Acquire as much
experiences in diverse parts of the
world and so on as you can first 20
years of your adult life at least.
That's what you should do. Don't make
any trade-offs. Always take the best
options.
Okay. So let's say by the time you're 40
you have tremendous experience in
various domains. You have a tremendous
skill set, a very robust skill set and
you have made millions of dollars. You
are a wealthy person.
How about you then think of let's say
you come back to India and contribute in
some way. Yeah. So I would say take the
best option that's available to you
from a selfish perspective. Right.
That's what I would say. [snorts]
Achintan says, "What if we were united
during the 8th century and had
reconquered Persia after the Arabic
invasion?" Well, then things would have
been different, I suppose.
Yeah. Uh see, we would not have
reconquered Persia. We would have
liberated Persia
after the Arabic invasion. In that case,
we had never conquered Persia before.
India, Persia, never tried to conquer
each other. Never. Ever. Um
[clears throat] so what if we were
united in the 8th century? Maybe the
Gupta Empire, let's say hypothetically,
was still the most powerful empire. It
was still united. and we decided that we
will kick the Arabs out of Persia and
liberate Persia. In that case, the world
would be very different today. Very very
very very very very different.
That's the answer. Chanaka 77 says Hindu
population dropped to 75% and projected
to be less than 50% in the next 50
years. How to save our future Hindus
from horrible fate by hands of Islam?
Isam. Look, look, I don't discuss Hindu
Muslim matters. I don't
So I'll not take this up. I'm very
sorry. I do not as a matter of policy
discuss Hindu Muslim issues. There are
plenty of channels that do that. I will
discuss history, geopolitics and
science. I will not go into this
matters. So I am very sorry that you
have asked me this question and you paid
for it but I will not be able to take
this question. I apologize sir.
Shashank says,
"Why does your map show Kashmir intact,
not mine?
Why does Okay, you mean the map that I
put on the screen?"
Um,
[clears throat]
why does this map show Kashmir intact?
Um
I
suppose it's because I am running this
out of India and in India Google is
behaving itself and showing uh Kashmir
as part of India. But if you change the
IP address to that of of a non-Indian
country, you're going to have a
different version of Kashmir shown from
Google itself. Yeah. So I suppose that's
the answer.
HP Patel says why does the Indian
government still use Mr. Gandhi's image
on currency despite his anti-Indian role
and shouldn't second October be removed
as public holiday
well the Indian government still uses
Mr. Mr. Gandhi's image
on Indian currency because the Indian
government still
regards Mr. Gandhi is the father of the
nation. The great Mahatma who liberated
India from from British occupation
through entirely nonviolent means.
The government of India still regards
Mr. Gandhi as a great hero as a savior.
Right? And that's why you have statues
of Mr. Gandhi. You have you know um the
honoring of Mr. Gandhi on the 2nd of
October every year without fail and so
on.
So that's why we have the situation.
Okay. Um, Dorji says, "Uh, small thank
you. I love your channel and content."
Thank you so much, Dori G. Thank you so
much. I really appreciate your your your
support and your wishes, your your your
your support and your positive wishes.
Thank you so much. Thank you so much
very much. Thank you very much indeed.
Abira Sharkkar says current large
language models don't perform well on
queries regarding non-public research
data. Do you think future stages of AI
maybe ASI will overcome this gap?
Okay. Current LLMs don't perform well on
queries regarding non-public research
data. Well, I would not know about this.
I've never tried that thing.
Interesting.
Uh see, I suppose large language models
are trained on public data. If some data
sets
uh research data sets have not been made
available to the public, if they are
confidential, then LLM will not be
trained on those.
At least LLMs that will be made
accessible to the public will never be
trained on those data sets. And LLMs
that will be trained on these
confidential data sets will be made
available to the government and to the
military.
Okay? And in the future if you have a
stage of AI which is an AS even AGI
stage but it's not been trained on those
data sets then maybe it will disregard
such research because it will not be
aware of it. But if you have AG or ASI
then it may be able to replicate this
rearch research on its own. So it will
not need that. So if you have ASI it
will have answers to everything. It will
not need to rely on the training data.
Even if some data is it has never been
trained on but it's available somewhere
this ASI will be able to replicate the
data and maybe improve upon that without
ever needing to access that.
Uh
Goo XXS says will India break into
pieces if regime changed well if there's
a regime change in India anything is
possible that's why a regime change must
not happen.
Hersh for says, "How to deal with fear
of missing out?" Fumo.
I'm not sure. Fear of missing out.
What is fear of I'm not very clear about
fear of missing out. But let me see what
Google has to say about what is FOMO.
What is fear of missing? Let's first see
that. What is
FOMO?
Anxiety that others have are having
rewarding experiences from which you are
absent. often fueled by seeing posts on
social media leading to a constant urge
to stay connected updated on whether
what others are doing. Uh pervasive
feeling that you're missing out on fun
opportunities or information important
information. You feel dissatisfied in um
or you compare yourself with others.
Social comparison, need for connection,
anxiety and stress impacting behavior.
What triggers it? Social media events,
financial markets and so on and so
forth. A nagging feeling that you should
be doing something else. Worry that you
made the wrong choice by not
participating. a sense that others are
living a better or more satisfying life.
How do you deal with this? I
couldn't possibly know.
Um
I don't know. Let me think. I can only
think about this theoretically because I
haven't experienced this. I don't
experience this. I don't have this
issue. Uh I don't compare myself with
others. I don't care what the others are
doing.
But how do you reach the stage where you
don't care what others are doing and you
just do what is best for yourself and
what you think I mean whatever you're
doing how do you do that
how to deal with for I I I I'm not sure
I'll have to think about this in in in
some detail it's not something that I
experience uh so I can't answer from
experience
and I haven't really thought about this
cuz
how would you deal yeah I think I'll
have to think about this in detail
without venturing an answer If I answer
something right now, it may not be
correct because I haven't thought about
it. So I am sorry I don't have the
answer right now. Please try asking this
maybe in a week's time. I will think
about it. What is the root cause of this
and so on? It it is obviously something
deeper inside in your psyche. There's
some deep rooted causes why people feel
this way and I will also think about why
I don't feel this way. See so I'll think
about it sir. I don't have the answer
right now. I I'm sorry for that.
Okay. uh
mangoserit
okay says do you think anything like
Venezuela can happen someday to India if
let's say any of the political parties
is in power it can happen yes it can
happen someday if we are not careful
yeah it can which is why we have to be
careful
we the public we the voters we the
leaders of India everybody has to do
whatever it takes in our own in our
different capacities to ensure sure that
such things don't happen because if we
are not careful this sort of thing can
happen to India also
Narendra Reddi says how to choose a life
partner most important decision
how to choose a life partner
see a life partner is somebody who's
going to be with you all your life so it
has to go beyond romantic or sexual
attraction
that obviously is a factor right you
will not want to marry somebody towards
whom you are not physically,
romantically or sexually attracted.
Obviously, you will want that. But that
cannot be the only factor.
You should be able to spend time without
getting annoyed with the person. You
should be mentally compatible. Your
ethics in your moral morals should be
compatible. Your worldview should be
compatible. You should be able to learn
from each other.
Everybody has some traits that are not
the best. So you should be able to
tolerate each other's flaws.
You should be able to sit with with each
other for hours in silence.
That's really hard.
Are you comfortable sitting with one
person with sitting next to one person
for one hour without saying a word? Are
you comfortable doing that?
It's very very uncomfortable with a lot
of people. So these are some of the
questions you to ask yourself. Okay?
It's it's somebody with whom you want to
spend the rest of your life. So these
all these factors have to come into
consideration not just how pretty or
handsome the person is it has to go
beyond that way beyond that you have to
be fundamentally compatible and that's
not easy to find but of course it's
possible right okay uh so so so Narendra
all the best all the best sir
shed light on Tavistock Institute crown
council committee of 30 300 sovereign
city of London if true where's the money
that was stolen from colonized empire
Paris couldn't send with correct
spelling. I don't know about any of
these.
I've heard Tavisto I mean the crown
council. I've heard I I got this
question earlier today. Committee of 300
sovereign city of London. I I don't
know. I I I genuinely honestly haven't
read about these things.
Um so I won't be able to answer this
question.
Maybe it's something I should look up
read about.
Yeah.
Yeah. So, so right now I don't have the
answer but uh maybe I'll look into that.
All right. The richest Pakistani says
untouchability sati child marriage in
Hinduism. Is it true?
Look
sati it happened sometimes. Very rare
thing it happened. Untouchability in
some parts of India at certain points in
time. There was some of that in the past
1,000 years. Before that, I can't think
of any
any widespread practice like that.
Today, you have do you have
untouchability in India? I mean, go to
any city in India. Go to a restaurant.
Does anybody care who's the waiter,
who's the server, who's the cook? Go to
a train station, go to a train, go to a
public transport in India. Doesn't even
care what the cast of the person next to
them. So, no one cares today.
Historically it may have happened here
and there but it's been you know blown
out of proportion. When a society come
under come comes under foreign
occupation for a thousand years all
kinds of defects creep into society
because of the leadership which is
oppressing the society because society
can't function the way it has evolved
naturally to function. Child marriage
well
you had child marriage all across the
world but yeah Hinduism is evil.
So look they've had Every every society
has pecularities
but we do not uh
okay that's I'll not give examples
what's the point I'd rather not uh D
Kamat says uh rather I would say that
physics probably proves that
consciousness is non-physical free will
must have a source which is non-physical
physics doesn't prove that consciousness
is not non-physical physics doesn't have
a definition of consciousness
Okay.
The issue is physics does not have a
definition of consciousness. We don't
have a definition of consciousness from
the perspective of let's say information
theory from the perspective of quantum
mechanics from the perspective of
general relativity. We don't have a
definition of free will from be of
consciousness from beyond physics for
from for example from the field of of of
neuroscience
or whatever. Yeah. So we don't have a
scientific definition of consciousness.
That is the issue. If you can't define
something, how can you prove it's
physical or non-physical? When you can't
even define it. If you want to talk
about something in physics, you have to
first define what it is. Only then you
can prove or disprove something. In
physics, we can't even define
consciousness. That is the first issue.
So if you can't define it, it's not
actually something you can even talk
about. That is the issue. That is the
issue. We all know, all of us know
trivially that consciousness exists. And
yet it's not so trivial because we can't
define it. That's the issue. That is the
most perplexing issue. It's something
profound.
So profound that anybody recognizes it
the moment you see it. There's a cat, of
of course it's conscious. There's a
crew, of course it's conscious. There's
a ant, of course it's conscious. There's
a cow of course is conscious another
person of course that person is
conscious the moment we see it we
recognize it instantaneously that's
conscious
but we can't define it rigorously from a
physical or scientific perspective we
can't define it we can define it from a
philosophical perspective there are all
kinds of things written about it but
from a scientific perspective we can't
define it which makes it incredibly
mysterious and profound
kartikaya says I used to think that maga
was Naga is more rational and has some
moral values left, but they are
defending murder of an innocent white
single mother in the hands of an IC
agent just because her hair is colored.
Well,
yeah. Well,
it is what it is.
The US is a police state
and the police has well essentially
unlimited powers. Yeah. and and these
things happen and obviously when
something like this happens uh and
there's a political dimension to it like
the color of your hair
then you have this happening and uh
yeah so they are saying that this was
self-defense or something which doesn't
I haven't really seen this but
apparently it doesn't seem to be the
case
um so yeah this is this is essentially
tribalism
tribalism and Yeah,
what can I say? It is what it is. Hersh
Patel says, "What are the root causes of
corruption in India? Has it existed
since ancient times? Despite good
salaries, officials demand bribes and
rich contractors deliver poor roads. Why
does this persist?
Has it existed? Has corruption existed
since ancient times?" Absolutely not.
Look up the shasta what it says about
corruption.
Intolerable. It will not tolerate
You think we had corruption during the
empires of Kaneska of the Guptas of the
Cholers
of the Marata Empire. Do you think do
you think we had corruption? Corruption
was never tolerated in India. Never
tolerated in India. Now why do we
allegedly have it? It was
institutionalized by the British.
The British created the the Indian
administrative system, right? to
administer the country to administer the
occupation and extraction and oppression
of the country. How do you administer
the oppression of the country? You
create a set of rules in the country.
And the in the Indian coolies, the
bureaucrats of Indian origin, they will
run the country for the white masters.
Now the Indian bureaucrats are are
instructed to have two sets of rules for
everything. If a white person needs
something, then the Indian bureaucrat
will do it immediately.
If an Indian person needs something,
demand bribes. Slow down the process.
Make it hard and feel the power that you
have. So this gives the Indian
bureaucrat the the the the sense that I
have I am a privileged Indian. My master
is the white man and I can oppress those
low
low Indians, Hindus. And this was
institutionalized.
The British created the the the British
uh judicial system, right?
If a British person needed a contract
had had a contract dispute, it went to
the court to the British British
judicial court. The the the case would
be resolved rapidly. If an Indian person
had a court case, ah it would drag and
drag and drag.
After the British left, there was no
white man to serve. Only brown people
coming for redressal or or problems of
solution of their solutions solutions of
their problems.
So I suppose that's how it continued,
right? It became institutionalized I
suppose allegedly.
So what's the solution?
No comments.
Um,
Karthikaya says, "I only learned now
after watching Star Talk that the sun is
white in color."
I'm not sure how many
videos are available
of the sun taken from the orbit from
orbit around the earth. Maybe a an
astronaut is in orbit around the earth
on the ISS, the International Space
Station, and they record their space
their spacew walks and whatnot, right?
In some of the videos, you'll see the
sun.
Check out the color of the sun from
space. It's always pure white. The sun
is a pure white star.
But why does it appear yellow to us?
H Why does the sky appear blue?
It's because of rail scattering.
It's because of an effect that you know
we know that the sun the white light is
made up of you know the different colors
altogether right vibio or roic whatever.
So um the atmosphere of the earth it
absorbs some some wavelengths and
scatters some wavelengths depending on
the angle at which the sun comes you
know the sun's light comes into the
atmosphere. So most of the time yellow
no the sky scatters blue and and and uh
so water also looks blue and the sky
also looks blue right but in the evening
and early morning the sky looks red
because of the amount of of uh
atmosphere that the sun's rays come
through the sun's light comes through so
it's because of the the different angles
at which and the the the thickness of
the atmosphere through which the light
is scattered
And the the atmosphere does contain
dust, grains and whatnot. Right? So
because of this you have the sun
appearing usually yellow in color. The
sunlight appearing yellow in color and
in the evenings and mornings appearing
red or deep orange in color. But the sun
actually is a white star and you can see
this in videos taken from orbit. It's
pure white.
Financial advisor for you says how is
Portuguese conversion different from
what we have going going on now in the
northeast. Is it any different at all?
Should we affiliate ourselves with Hindu
organizations as mandatory to prevent
conversions? See, Portuguese conversion
was pretty brutal.
The Portuguese converted by force. They
destroyed Hindu temples and built
churches on top of them. They imposed
laws that made it almost impossible to
remain Hindu and they burned Hindus
alive and did all kinds of horrific
atrocities. What's happening in the
northeast is is coercion. It's a
different kind of coercion.
um they use different methods. They
can't use the inquisition today, right?
So they have used other other methods.
See, they have targeted people who live
in isolated regions, who live in hills,
tribal people and so on, who don't have
the depth of culture and civilization
that people who don't live in isolated
groups generally have. So that's why the
missionaries always target tribals and
forest dwellers and hill dwellers first.
And when it comes to the far east of
India you know uh Nagaland and so on and
Mizoram and so on these people they have
been dwelling in hills and all for a
very long time and they the missionaries
find them easier to convert. So they
have converted them by making them feel
inferior that you people are backward
and your religion is backward you're
cannibals or you're this or that and our
god is superior and we will give you
wealth. will give you prestige and so on
which makes it very easy easy for such
people to convert and then you start
making life life difficult for those
people who are Hindus and they will also
slowly break over time which is what's
happening to the uh to the mate Hindus
of of Manipur now slowly they're also
beginning to convert uh so it's
different so the Portuguese conversion
was just brutal impossible it was just
slammed through what's happening in the
northeast and what's happened over the
past uh 60 70 80 years at the hands of
American Baptist missionaries is very
It's very devious.
Yeah. But at the end of the day, it has
the same effect of creating population
groups that are that develop extr
territorial loyalties. So should we do
this or that? That's entirely up to you.
But yeah,
Krishant Bordoy says you think 20 years
later US will confront us militarily.
No, the US doesn't want 20 years later.
If they want to confront us militarily,
they will do it in the next 5 years. 20
years later later is too late. It's too
late.
It's like trying to take your wicket
after you've scored 200 runs. No, no,
no, no, no. You do it when you on three
not out. So the US will not try to do
that to confront us literally 20 years
later. It'll be too late. By the time
we'll be able to stand up to them. If
they want to do this, they can they
should they will most likely do it in
the next 5 years. Okay. Rajat Gupta
says, "What's your opinion about
consciousness? We experience world
through the first person POV point of
view." I know about world. All I know
about the world is through me. Do I only
exist? Can we disprove it? What you are
talking about is soypism.
Uh cypism is the idea that the only mind
that exists in the universe is your own
mind. Whatever you exist, whatever you
experience, you experience through your
sense organs
transmitting electrical messages,
impulses to your brain.
Okay?
So your brain doesn't experience things
directly. Your mind doesn't experience
things directly. It experiences things
indirectly through your sense organs and
the electrical messages those sense
organs send to your brain. What if your
sense organs are hallucinating this
information?
And what if the entire universe that you
are experiencing is just an illusion
created by your own brain?
What if you are the only
entity, conscious entity in existence?
Well, that's that's kind of the solistic
line of thinking. Um, so yeah,
everything you know about the world is
through me. Do you only exist? Well,
that's a philosophical question. Um, can
we disprove it? We can't disprove it.
[laughter]
See, philosophy is logical. So, what's
my opinion about consciousness? What is
my opinion about consciousness? Well, it
does exist.
Um, consciousness obviously exists.
What's the source of consciousness? I'm
not quite sure.
I may have some idea. I mean, I may have
a hunch. I may have
some intuition about it.
But those in that intuition is obviously
non-scientific because we don't have a
definition of consciousness. Maybe maybe
it's likely that there is a
consciousness field across the universe.
Maybe it's a it's a maybe. This is a
philosophical thought. This is
philosophical music. It's not scientific
musing. Philosophy is a science is a
subset of philosophy. I am thinking
philosophically here. I'm not thinking
in terms of science because
consciousness the discussion around
consciousness is not within the realm of
science. It's within the realm of
philosophy. So maybe what if there's a
there's a consciousness field that
permeates the universe. Just like we
have 17 different fields for each of the
subatomic particles, you know,
fundamental particles of of the certain
model. What if we have a consciousness
field? Maybe what if it's something that
you know our current science can't
detect or or can't even define. Yeah.
And maybe some
some configurations of of matter maybe
they focus the consciousness into
something that actually [laughter]
that uh that that that that that you
know that occurs locally in in one
location just like excitations in the
field are particles you know in various
fields are particles in quantum field
theory. Maybe that that could be one
theory that we can think about but we
don't have an answer about uh
consciousness as such.
Okay. Um An Divu says, "Sar your
geostrategy shows were amazing. Have you
considered reviving it on Indian news
channels rather than YouTube or going to
Rumble?" Um I haven't considered that.
Indian news channels. Well, if you go on
an Indian news channel, you have to
abide by the rules and um the
constraints that uh they face because of
their funding and what not. I'm not sure
what's the point of doing it on some
news channel. Will they even want me
because I will have to abide by their
editorial lines and all that which I'm
not sure I want to.
Oh, Rumble. I'm not sure if anybody will
even watch Rumble. I'm not sure if
Indian knows about Indians know about
Rumble. I may have like three people
watching me if I do it there. Uh we'll
see about that. Maybe I can restart it
eventually. Maybe we'll we'll see. I'll
think about it. But uh thank you very
much for your feedback indeed. Thank
you. H Patel says, "Why does India still
store about 290 tons of golds of its
gold reserves overseas even under the
current pro-India government? I think we
stored a tremendous amount of gold in
the Bank of London and so on during the
uh time when we had this financial issue
and we opened up our economy in the
early '90s, right? And the storage of
gold in these bank of London and whatnot
is a legacy issue and the current
pro-India government has been
repatriating the gold steadily back from
from the bank of London or Bank of
England or whatever it is slowly
steadily over time. So earlier it was
much more now it's only 290 tons of
whatever
and
I'm pretty sure we will repatriate that
also back steadily over the next let's
say weeks, months or whatever. I agree
with you. It should be done. it should
entirely be repatriated to India. Why do
we need to have even one gram of gold in
a foreign bank? So I agree with you and
uh that's what should be done and I'm
sure it will be done soon.
SJ boy says please tell us more about
vasilization probability
whose Pakistan's Iran's India's watch
India I think the probability is low but
not zero maybe I don't know next 5 years
is the break make or break time what's
the probability of facilization I would
say 25% or something yeah and one hopes
it doesn't happen because it's going to
be the make or break time for India
because the US is going to put all of
its might all of its leverage on India
to attempt to vasalize India because it
doesn't want India to to rise as the
next China and it wants access to the
huge Indian market to plunder the hell
out of us. Yeah. So
Sahil Singh says thanks for your efforts
in explaining things so nicely. How to
master English communication like you?
How do you master
um how do you master playing tennis? You
play tennis. You get better, a little
bit better every day. How do you master
playing the guitar? You start as a
complete beginner. You keep playing,
let's say, practicing 1 hour a day. In
30 days, you're going to be way better
than a beginner. You keep doing it for 3
years, you're going to be an
intermediate to expert level guitarist.
How do you get better at something?
Not by reading about it, but by doing
it, by practicing it. So if you want to
master Portuguese communication, you
want to master Japanese comm
communication, you want to master the
English communication, practice it. Do
it every day. If you want to master
becoming a good communicator in English,
verbal communication,
stand in front of the mirror and speak
for half an hour every day or grab two
or three of your friends, put them in
chairs and speak to them half an hour
every day. And every day ask for their
feedback. What have I done that can be
improved? What are my strong points?
What are the points that need
improvement? Get the feedback even
though it's uncomfortable and try and
implement what they're saying and and
make things better. So that's how we do
it. Sir, all the best. Karthikar says,
"Your practical and sensible idea of
buying Greenland by the US by paying a
million dollars per resident a few few
months back was discussed in the White
House as per rumors on X.
[laughter]
What on earth? I remember saying this
many months ago. Just pay each of these
residents a million dollars.
I think it's a practical and sensible
idea. If you are the US, just pay them a
million dollar each. That's what $60
million peanuts or 60 $6 billion or
whatever. There are 60,000 people on in
Greenland. 60,000 times 1 million.
That's that's 60,000 million. That's 60
billion. That's nothing. The US can
afford it very very much afford it. So
was it discussed in the White House.
All right. I'm well glad to be of
service.
Sir Donald.
[laughter]
Okay. Sed Singh Raj Prahad says you are
a secretive person. We don't know much
about you. What's your routine? When
were you born? Where do you live?
Married kids? How to meet you? Is all
classified information. You see I
actually am alien invader.
I am a leanian. Everything about me is
classified. It is not for public
consumption. You see, you have to keep
some sense of mystery about yourself.
[laughter]
Oh no, no, no, no. Mystery, mystery.
Pawar says, "Is the event horizon
physically real?" No.
See, let's say you are an astronaut and
you are falling towards a black hole and
you cross the event horizon. If it's a
if it's super massive black hole, let's
if it's a small black hole, you will
know immediately before the event
horizon comes at you something is going
wrong with you very badly wrong with you
and very painfully wrong with you. You
will start becoming spaghettified. But
if it's a big massive super massive
black hole, very gold ancient one, then
if you are crossing the event horizon,
you won't even realize it. There is no
signpost over there. Hi, you are now
crossing the event horizon. Nothing like
that. So it's not physically real. There
is no such boundary or membrane there
that you feel when you cross nothing.
But it's very physically real in the
sense that once you cross that the
escape velocity exceeds C the speed of
light and you simply can't return. And
then as you fall further towards the
center of the black hole you start
experiencing not so pleasant things. And
well there's nothing you can do once you
cross the horizon. All right.
Hor Patel says in breaking the mold,
Raguram Rajan argues that government
should prioritize R&D or manufacturing
to capture greater value citing Apple
and Foxcon. What I what's my opinion
about this? I don't take anything Mr.
Rauram Rajan says seriously.
That's my straightforward and simple
opinion about anything Mr. Rauram Rajan
says. I don't take this gentleman
seriously.
Okay, that's it.
Um, Ritiagi says, "Can you explain
Einstein's idea that past, present, and
future all existed once?" I'm not sure
Einstein ever said that. Did Einstein
ever said that? I
don't think Einstein ever said that. Let
us see if Google can tell us. Did
Einstein ever say
Did
Einstein say that past, past, present,
and future all exist at once? Did
Einstein say that? Good Lord,
he said that. So he said that the
distinction between past, present, and
future is only a stubbornly persistent
illusion. That seems like a wise crack
or something.
Okay. A view supported by his theory of
relativity. The concept of a block
universe where all moments exist in
unified space time through our
consciousness. Though our consciousness
perceives time is fleeing. I'm not sure
what Google's AI is saying over here.
So in in relativity we do have you know
a fourdimensional universe.
Um and one of the dimensions is time
right past, present, future. when there
are word lines of particles and all I'm
not sure if it says that Einstein did
say this right
and we know that
there's something called the
simultaneity of the the relativity of
simultaneity
which is something that emerges out of
special relativity the relativity of
simultaneity which means that if I am
sitting here and I observe two things
happening simultaneously two stars going
supernova at the same time
simultaneously and you were sitting
somewhere else like 20 million light
years away for you that those two events
may not happen simultaneously.
So from that perspective maybe past,
present, future are not exactly the same
thing for everybody depending on where
you are. Do they exist all at once? Not
necessarily. I'm not sure if he was
making this as a
uh if if he did say this. Google is
saying he said that
um
but I'm not sure he was being entirely
serious about this. Yeah, there are
people I mean even scientists great
scientists sometimes make jokes or make
wise cracks that don't exactly
are to be interpreted literally or
seriously.
So in in relativity you can have two
event events happening for one observer
from their perspective s simultaneously
or for another observer that may not
happen simultaneously but that doesn't
necessarily mean that past present
future all exist at once that that is
not what it means.
Okay. Uh Firefly says what does the
elimination of perceived evil? No. Why
does the elimination of perceived evil
result in simply more evil? Like you
mentioned Bengal in Egypt.
Similar happened when Julius Caesar was
killed. I mentioned Bengal in Egypt. The
elimination of perceived evil.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. I
mentioned Bengal. Uh Sirajadullah was
ousted and the Bengalists thought that
Clive was the savior but he was actually
more evil. Egypt. They thought that the
Persians were evil. But then Alexander
ended up being more evil. Julius Caesar
was killed because he was going to be
the dictator. But then you had his his
adopted son Augustus who became exactly
what they did not want Julius to become.
Is that always the case? It's not
necessarily always the case. Sometimes
the elimination of perceived evil is the
elimination of real evil. It's not a
rule of thumb that it is always like
that.
Right?
I mean when Krishna, Lord Krishna killed
K's mama,
it was genuinely the elimination of
evil. The evil was perceived but it was
also real, right? So it's not always the
case. It's not a rule of thumb.
Sometimes it can go wrong like that.
Maybe in Kalyug that's what happens more
often than not. Uh Rajat says, "Can
right-handed neutrons be DM?" Why not
left-handed neutrinos? DM is dark
matter. Neutronos are not dark matter
because we can detect neutronos.
Neutronos are not dark matter. Yeah,
dark matter is something that can't be
detected
except for through its gravitational
interaction. But there are some theories
of dark matter having a weak component,
you know, part of the weak sector.
Yeah. Like axons or whatever. But I
don't really put too much. I personally
am not a big fan of those theories. Of
course it's that's a personal opinion
but neutrinos are not considered to be
part of dark matter. We can detect
neutrinos. We have experiments super
kamio and what not that do detect
nutrinos. So now kiran mory says India
has lot of oil and gas in the Anderman
in and nicobar but Indian government
doesn't make it public because US try to
control it. We we don't talk about these
things. No no I I know nothing about
this. We do not talk about this.
A Rahul says why Aiawaska and other
cultural Indian psycho psychedelic
alternatives are illegal in India and
most of the world. They have been used
for spiritual purposes for ages.
Um ayawaska it's some kind of a ritual
ceremony with some psychedelic
ingredients that is conducted by shamans
in the Amazon rainforest, right? And it
causes you to have visions and have some
physical things and you
you you experience things that obviously
exist only in your inner universe and
obviously it's a very strong psychedelic
experience and so on and I is it illegal
in most of the world I'm not sure
whether it's legal or not in what part
of the world I suppose in India
everything is illegal because India
simply blindly copies the west if it is
illegal in the west the west must be
right they are White people they do
things right. So we will simply copy
them. Simply copy them. That's what we
do in India. So if the west bans
marijuana weed, we in India should ban
it. West is doing it. It should be bad.
We had this tradition for thousands of
years that people consumed marijuana on
specific days or nights like Shivatri
and so on. But no, we have to ban it. So
India is a nation of slave-minded
people, slave mentality. in India simply
blindly copies the west in so many
things is ayawaska harmful to society
is it addictive it's not addictive I
don't think if somebody does goes
through that experience once they want
to go through that again I don't think
it's a very very comfortable experience
as far as what I've heard
so I don't know I don't know why India
does a lot of what India does has no
logic behind it you know it's just slave
mentality
bordoy says ruling part is asking Hindus
to have four kids no thoughts no
thoughts sorry sir no thoughts I don't
even know if it's true or not but no
thoughts
a Rahul says was analyzing present
society through game theory who's the
real designer of the status game or who
gains most out of it possible hidden
players
I
you must have tremendous mathematical
skills if you can analyze society
through game theory society has so many
variables
I would imagine you need a supercomput
incredible amounts of computing power to
analyze society through game theory. I'm
not sure how do how doing it. I don't
know how to do it. I have some
understanding of game theory. I have
some actual understanding of game
theory. I don't know how to analyze
society through that. Maybe you can play
toy games, you know, two people, two
person, three person games and uh use
that as a model for the larger society.
Perhaps you can do it that way. you
know, reduce complex
nplayer society to a, let's say,
three-player game or something. That
sort of thing you can do and then you
can extrapolate those the the results to
society at large. But that doesn't
always work correctly, right? Um, so the
question now you're asking is who's the
real designer of the of the status game?
I think status games are inherent to
human society.
If you are
an observer, you know,
if you are a deep observer of human
society and interactions, you will
realize that every human human
interaction at some level is an is a
status interaction.
You may not see it that way. You may not
believe in high status, low status, but
probably the other person believes in
that.
Most people do. Who gains out of it?
Possibly hidden players. Who gains out
of it? High status players always gain
compared to low status players. And why
do people have high high status? Because
of various perceived qualities, things
etc. Maybe they've given more value to
society which gives them high status.
Maybe they have things that society
desires which which gives them high
status. Maybe they have power which
gives them high status. Then those
people always have the advantage in in
these games.
Possible hidden players. Well, of
course, there are hidden players and
hidden variables and so on, but with
unless you explain the parameters of the
game and how many players you're dealing
with and what the rules are, I can't
really tell you
what exactly you're discussing here, you
know, if you're if this is a game
theoretic discussion.
Okay.
Uh Rahul says, why are Indians
passionate commenters not doers? Because
this is what is ingrained into us
through our education system. Talk talk.
Argue, argue, argue, criticize,
criticize, criticize, nit, nitpick,
nitpick, nitpick. Don't do anything.
Okay? If you want to have a class in
physical education, you have to write
essays about physical education and talk
about physical education and point out
flaws in the other guy's essay. But
don't actually do physical education.
If you want to have if you want to be
regarded as an expert in let's say ODC
dance, you need to get a PhD in ODC
dance by writing long long thesis about
ODC dance. Not by being an actual
highquality performer of ODC dance. It's
all about talk talk talk in India. The
entire education system
dumps this inertia, drills this inertia
into your heads. All you have to do in
India to be regarded as an expert in
something is to talk talk talk talk and
criticize and point out flaws and do
nitpicking.
Okay, your experts can talk the most
complex things, the most complicated
language. Can they actually solve
problems? Most of them can't. It's
entirely because of the education
system. Entirely because of that.
Okay. Way of Tombbur says, "I loved
reading a book you had recommended, A
New History of Life by Peter Ward and
John Kushnik.
Can you suggest more books which go into
deep time?"
Um, deep.
>> Um,
don't recall any any of those right now.
Yeah.
Yeah. Right now I don't have any
recommendations. I I have to think about
it. If I can do the I can think about
something I may post it on social media
or something. Check Check it out. Um
yeah, right now I can't think of any.
Sorry about that. Uh Fastnail says
thoughts on Scientology, inspiration
from Hinduism. Scientology, inspiration
from science fiction. I don't know about
inspiration from Hinduism. Inspiration,
the inspiration for Scientology seems to
be entirely from 1960s and 50s science
fiction.
I don't see personally any inspiration
from Hinduism unless it is tangential or
indirect. It's just pure science fiction
the way I see it. Yeah. Ab Shark says,
"How do Modi or CEOs avoid burnout when
busy?" I don't know.
How do you avoid burn out?
How do you avoid burnout? What is
burnout? Like your brain is overworked
and it genuinely needs a break, right?
How do you avoid that?
You
how do you avoid burnout?
I suppose you do you balance things that
you do. So let's say for example if you
are writing a book you just keep on
writing writing right you get burned out
right after writing four hours a day
about one topic you genuinely get burned
out mentally and if you do that for two
months on end every day four hours you
write then you may get burned out. So
what do you do the rest of the time? Do
something else totally different. Maybe
play guitar. Maybe go for a jog. Maybe
spend 1 hour lifting weights or
something. Do something totally
different which is also positive, which
is also constructive. So that's how you
can avoid burnout. If you're a CEO,
you have multiple responsibilities. So
spend two hours on this, spend two hours
on that,
do some you have to simply balance
things out effectively. And if you can
do that properly, if you're really good
at that, you will avoid burnout, I
suppose. And that's what Yeah. Mr. Modi
actually needs only I believe four hours
of sleep. So I think he has plenty of
time to balance things out. Uh yeah
says the Indian army has shot down a
Pakistani drone. Let's find out. Yeah.
Let's see. Indian Oops. Indian ar Indian
army Pakistani drone.
Okay. Multiple drone incursion attempts.
Okay. Months after operation the Indian
army opens fire on Pakistani drones.
Okay. So the Pakistanis are back to
their old tricks. Okay. We will I
suppose we will deal with them. Yeah.
Whipple power says are black holes
optimal data compressors. We don't know
what happens to the data. If it's
compressed and then it's given back in
its original shape and form. Well, in
that case these are optimal data
compressors possibly. Uh but what
happens to the data? Is it actually
destroyed?
Does it come out in a completely
incomprehensible
and in uncorreable uncorrelatable
u
form? So
can't really say if black holes are
optimal data compressors. Do they just
destroy the data?
So let's say a photon goes in with a
certain kind of polarization
or a particle goes in that is spin up.
What happens with the information that
it has spin up? Does it come out in some
some shape or form?
It can come out in the shape of Hawking
radiation which is black body radiation
completely random radiation.
So does it mean the data was scrambled
or is the data just simply destroyed? We
don't know. I've heard people say that
the black hole information paradox has
been mostly resolved. I'm not sure how
it has. So I can't really say that black
holes are optimal data compressors. If
we can resolve the black hole
information paradox satisfactory
satisfactorily
and explain in what shape or form the
data is scrambled and then thrown out
again in a way that's retrievable then
we could potentially say that the black
holes are really optimal data
compressors but I am not sure we are at
that stage right now. So at this stage
in in time no
readyy always ready says can you please
do at least one geopolitical episode per
week? Well, if everyone wants that, I'll
be happy to do it. So, I'm doing one
geopolitical episode, which is also half
geopolitics, half history, which is what
I did on Friday, which I generally do on
Saturdays. Um,
I I I can do it. I'm I'm happy to do it
if if everybody wants that. Yeah. So,
let me know in the comments below or in
the in the super chat. I mean, the the
regular chat if that's what you want. If
you want, I'm happy to oblige. I am at
your service. I'm at your disposal.
Absolutely.
Okay. Brahma Mosqua says, "Brahamos,
is there a possibility of ousting the
Americans of the Garcia and diminishing
all?" No. No. Can't even dream of it
right now. Can't even dream of it as of
right now. Right now, don't even dream
of it. Don't even think of it. Keep
quiet. Do your thing. India needs to
quietly
quietly increase its strength, economic
and military power and hard power. right
now. Don't even think of challenging the
Americans in any shape or form.
Absolutely not. No possibility.
Okay. Uh a Rahul says, "I realized many
of my passions were manufactured by PR
and money to look cool." Yeah, that that
happens to a lot of people.
Everybody in some shape or form is is is
you know falls prey to this sort of
thing. So who shapes these trends and
why do we become labor or freak? Why do
we become labor or freak for freak for
fake prestige? Who shapes these trends?
The corporations and governments shape
these trends. The west is purely
capitalistic. The west means it's run by
the US. The US corporations want to
maximize shareholder value, want to
maximize profits. They shape these
trends. They sometimes seed the trends
20, 30 years in advance,
right? And they make these things cool
and they target the youngsters who still
aren't experienced enough to to
recognize this for what it is, right?
and they then end up being the labor for
pre prestige. The younger you are, the
more susceptible you are to these
things. We are we have all been through
that.
So these trends are shaped. They're
seeded by the big big big billion
trillion dollar corporations. That's
that's who does that.
Fast snail says Professor Sax in an
interview with Arnab said things you say
100%.
Good job, Professor Saxs. What can I
say? [laughter]
Okay. All right. All right. Okay. Uh
Rajat says, "I said right-handed
neutrons, not left." I thought you said
left. Okay. You said right. Okay. Uh
please Google. Uh right-handed
neutronos. Rightanded
neutrino
dark matter. How is it dark matter?
Let's see.
Okay. Why chain? What does he say on
archive? The ceso mechanism with three
right-handed neutrons has one and one as
a well motivated dark matter candidate
if stable and the other two can explain
barrier asymmetry by the thermal
process. We explore the possibility of
additional of introducing additional
particles to make the right-handed
neutron dark matter in thermal
equilibrium and freeze through of
the
PDF. Let me see the introduction. The
heavy right-handed mayorana neutrinos
are widely considered a key ingredient
beyond the stand beyond the standard
model of physics. They explain not only
the observed tiny neutrinoes by the so
okay okay I will not go through the
process of reading everything heavy
sterile neutrinos that don't interact by
the weak force like normal nutrinos. Oh
the heavy sterile neutrinos could be the
elusive dark matter.
Okay.
Okay. It's an idea. Okay. We'll see.
We'll see.
I I don't consider neutrons to be a
serious dark matter candidate. I think
we are clutching at straws right now at
this point in time. You know things are
not working out. We aren't able to make
breakthroughs. So we are now clutching
at straws and saying sterile neutrons
and so on so forth dark matter. Okay.
All right.
Uh Rahul says why are religions trying
to portray themselves as scientific?
This why do religions have to try and
portray themselves as scientific?
Cultural traditions don't need science
validation but people are afraid.
I think it is only some religions that
are I no actually it's I think yeah
there are multiple religions that are
trying to portray themselves as
scientific look religion and science
are different things
some I would say religion should try to
portray themselves if they can prove if
they can that they are philosophical not
scientific
science and religion don't mix
but religion can be philosophical
If it it takes some amount of intellect
to understand that religions that good
religions are philosophical
but not scientific.
What's the difference?
If a religion is philosophical, it's a
great religion. Philosophy has logic.
Philosophy is is is is
logically sound.
Okay, religion if it is philosophical,
it is logically sound. It is logically
self-contained. It doesn't break its own
logic.
But non-filosophical religions are just
about they believe in this, have faith.
There is no further explanation.
Right? Philosophy has logic. It has
rules and those rules have to be
self-contained, self-sufficient.
Um [snorts]
and science is a subset of philosophy.
So religions if they can should prove
that they are philosophical in nature.
They should not need to they don't have
to prove that they are scientific. But
people the overwhelming majority of
people don't understand the difference
between science philosophy and religion
and religion can be philosophical. It
doesn't have to be scientific.
Brahma Mosqu says ousting
um M of DG in the ousting
somebody of Diego Garcia in the Indian
Ocean. How and when? Are you saying
ousting the US
of Diego Garcia in the Indian Ocean? How
and when? Not anytime soon. Not anytime
near soon. No,
not possible today. Not possible anytime
soon. So let's not discuss that. Is it
not possible? They're too powerful. Too
powerful. Okay, next question. Krishnant
Bordaloy says Masur Basud Azar said he
will attack India. Thoughts? Haha.
Try
try buddy. Try try try
that's all I'll say
you.
No need to go that go that route. Okay.
Sergeant Skylon. Hi. Long long time no
see. Long time no see. Good to see you.
Sergeant Skylon sir or ma'am. So I
suppose it's it's a it's a gentleman,
right? Maybe maybe you'll never know
this is but yes, long time no see. Good
to have you back. Good to see you.
All right, that brings me to the end of
today's live stream. We have almost
touched 4 hours. So I end this I hereby
I herew with end this live stream the
321st live stream of the Ask a Bijit
show. Thank you so much. Thank you very
much everybody for all your questions.
Keep learning, keep asking questions,
keep raising your standards, and I will
see you in next week's live streams.
Look forward to seeing you then. Take
care.